Youtube subtitles download by mo.dbxdb.com
Khan are we good all right so greetings
and welcome everybody to this first
exciting edition of 15 18 to 13 or 15
5:13 why are you laughing at me so what
to say here we are and the other end of
the camera there you are hope we're all
happy to be Robin you know I'm happy to
be here
this is one of my favorite classes to
teach I mean this class has a lot of all
sorts of different things that are
really really really useful right it's
like a candy box of useful stuff because
it's samples right important things from
all of our systems systems classes right
to get you sort of ready and exposed to
material while teaching some really
critically important hi some really
critically important system skills okay
so really is an important class and I
love teaching it because it's it's so
applied and so much fun okay um what to
say the course theme you know if you're
an undergraduate student or ever were an
undergraduate student in computer
science you may remember that at the
beginning of your education we talked a
lot about abstraction okay we worked a
lot with abstractions this idea that if
you have really complex systems what you
want to do is encapsulate certain
functionality make it into black boxes
and ignore it that if you're trying to
understand something really really
really really really complex
you can't possibly grok all the details
at once so you assemble meaningful
bullet building blocks whether they're
actual real tangible building blocks
like building a building out of concrete
blocks as opposed to you know as opposed
to concrete or right code-wise building
blocks like modules and libraries or
intellectual building blocks like Big O
and amortized analysis right and so we
focus a lot on
you're acting things to get powerful
things you know represented in a way in
which we can use it and this is a great
tool that's important to every aspect of
computer science apply the theoretical
okay and it's one that's used from
freshman year all the way through
graduate education and you know careers
in the computer sciences but sometimes
in narrow areas you actually need to
blow through those abstractions you
actually need to get down to the details
with it's measuring actual performance
and actual time rather than throwing
away that pesky constant right we're
thinking about how something runs or is
running on a real computer and that's
for two thirteen is about two thirteen
is about doing it for real okay
why well a to become effective
programmers right and be to be effective
students right we do it because it's a
critically important skill to the
practical programmer we also do it B's
is a critically important skill to
learning more advanced computer science
most especially in systems but also in a
ton of other areas right graphics
databases all sorts of things okay we've
got though a bunch of slides here about
these great realities I don't spend a
whole bunch of time on these great
realities right now because we spend the
whole semester diving into the details
but perhaps they're a good example of
abstraction in real-world detail when
you were in math classes you learned
about integers right the set of all
integers and integers were really cool
right because they were a countably
infinite of them no matter what energy
you give me I can give you something
bigger and no matter what energy you
give me I can give you something smaller
right amazing and there's space between
them you can't get there
but computers don't quite work that way
right computers have a finite amount of
memory they don't have an infinite
amount of memory they have a finite
amount of memory
yeah much how big is much is J much I
don't know how much memory do you have
in that computer but once we start
dealing with real world and real world
limits finite memory that means we need
to have a finite representation of a
number right if I only have a much
memory the bin the you know in one case
I can use it all for a single number
that's probably not really useful right
I probably want to partition it so I
could have more than one thing in memory
and say well my memories yay big my
integers that most can be a big and now
we start to have real limits
maybe an integer can only go from let's
say negative 32,000 or so to positive 32
thousand or so now so now we're talking
about a difference between intz right
the integer representation we have
available in programming are you
recording class yes no we provide the
only recording turn that off so go ahead
and interject right now there is a
policy against electronically mediated
communication and recording okay so
you're not allowed to I am text email
web surf join chat rooms IRC
collaboratively edit documents blah blah
blah blah blah
no electronically mediated communication
so you can use your laptop to take notes
you can use your laptop to look at
slides if you downloaded them in advance
okay but no electronically mediated
communication secondly the only
recording of this class is the one that
we take you will have access it to it to
this semester in this semester only and
then it goes away ok and the reason for
that is very obvious you guys are
enrolled students you're taking 15 to 13
or 15 5/13 and quite honestly you're
paying us for it we're not delivering
these videos for free ok 15 to 13 has a
canonical set of lectures it has a
canonical set of labs
that's the canonical set of auto graders
these days it has an inker ever growing
set of exam questions and you know exam
graders no one out there is gonna take
our set of materials and distribute them
and call it a Carnegie Mellon equivalent
program it's not right because doesn't
have you as a collection of students it
doesn't have our course staff as a
collection of people supporting it right
and we're just not going in that
direction so for this semester you'll
have access to all the video once you're
done the video goes away if you want to
refer to things after that you've got
your notes and you've got the book and
you've got the slides but there's no
recording okay we good all right and no
electronically mediated communication
here so if you want to have fun it's got
to be you know my type of fun all right
back to this so once we have finite
memory right what to say now we can't
have infinite number of integers right
we have relatively few number of
integers so what happens if we have the
biggest int that we can represent and we
add one to it it's not going to get
bigger right different answers to that
question are possible maybe it goes into
an error state flags that is a number
that's too high
that happens with floating point numbers
actually with integers as you pointed
out it wraps around and becomes the most
negative number and we'll talk about why
okay
but this is a classic example of why
sometimes you've got to be able to look
through abstraction into the detail
because intz right look a lot like
integers work a lot like integers for a
lot of problems there are great
substitute for integers and then
suddenly things don't work the way you
think they should and when they don't
work the way you think they should now
you've got to actually understand why
how they're implemented right why it's
implemented that way and how you can
make things work that way okay
another issue right and it's less of an
issue most of the time and then
sometimes it matters right there's no
such thing as randomness when it comes
to a computer okay at best we have some
approximation of randomness right what
happens right there's something called a
pseudo-random number generator
it's a function where the values bounce
around in a way that you really wouldn't
predict unless you were using the same
function and then we pick some starting
point along this it's called the seed
and now we get a sequence of seemingly
random numbers so unless you know the
generator and you know the seed it looks
like a random set of numbers okay and
then how do we pick that seed well what
we try to do is get things from outside
the computer then approximate random
things because outside the computer
there are random numbers or randomness
at least and so we try to use things
like the measure of time between ports
coming to the between Bo packets showing
up at the network or you know the value
and time between keystrokes and and and
and and take a whole bunch of system
events coming from different sources
that don't have the same force function
and hopefully have no discernable force
function and use those to generate a
sequence of numbers that we can then use
to seed our random number generator why
not just use these random things because
aren't enough of them if we need a whole
bunch of random numbers we can't collect
enough randomness there's no infinite
improbability generator here okay so we
use external events that are hopefully a
random or approximately random tusu to
de-seed pseudo-random number generators
sometimes it matters sometimes doesn't a
lot of times a random number generator
number of pseudo-random number generator
is just as good as real random numbers
sometimes it's better if something
random is a provider's input to your
program and then your program dies you
may have no way of figuring out what
that was it was some random event right
but if we're actually using a
pseudo-random
number generator we could provide the
same seed and get the same set of events
much better free debugging right to have
pseudo randomness than real randomness
of course that predictability isn't good
then different story right okay um so
back in the day well before my day
people used to actually write
significant volumes of assembly by hand
right when you look at an assembly file
the extension on an assembly file is dot
s right dot C for C dot J for Java right
why is assembly dot s and not dot a well
the answer is because back in the day it
was the source code s source people
wrote assembly by hand and then fed it
to an assembler okay to get the machine
code and for a long time even after
compilers became a thing right a lot of
code was still written in assembly
because quite simply compilers weren't
good enough they could generate code you
know assembly code from high-level code
but couldn't do it really really
efficiently they couldn't do it really
really efficiently for two reasons Hey
the science of writing compilers just
hadn't advanced as much and B computers
weren't fast enough okay compilers now
build a lot of data structures and
analyze a lot of different possibilities
to determine the optimal ones when
computers were really slow it wasn't
worth it
no one wondered wait a week for a
compile okay
but these days computers are much faster
the science of writing compilers is much
better we can write really really
efficient compilers and beyond that
processors have gotten so complicated
that humans trying to understand how to
code for them efficiently suffer from
state explosion we just can't keep all
of the possibilities all of those states
in their head so humans can't possibly
write
code as efficiently in assembly as
compilers can there are certain small
bits of assembly that humans still write
by hand okay
very small bits usually in the depth of
an operating system or embedded system
but other than that all code starts out
as a high-level code now that doesn't
mean the programmers don't need to be
able to read assembly in fact we do
because the assembly what's at is what's
actually executing sometimes it's good
enough to look at the high-level code
and assume the assembly does the same
thing but sometimes the details actually
matter and then we need be able to blow
through that abstraction and read the
assembly to understand what the Machine
is actually going to do when it's
executing our program okay so you know
in a traditional engineering class when
one learned assembly one actually
learned assembly by writing it writing a
bunch of assembly language programs we
don't do that here because it's not
useful no one writes a bunch of assembly
language programs even those people who
code in assembly don't write programs
that could be written in high-level code
in assembly that's not useful what we're
gonna learn here to do is read assembly
and understand assembly and understand
what the assembly is asking the machine
to do and understand how that assembly
relates to our C code that way we can
program and see and understand what
we're asking the machine to do for real
when we need to when we care and we can
double check our abstract understanding
with a detailed understanding whenever
we choose to by diving deep for
applications like you know tuning
performance writing the you know the the
the really detailed bits and hardware
dependent bits of operating systems and
embedded systems things like fighting
malware and viruses and in very very
very rare cases dealing with program
bugs but those are pretty rare cases
most of the time the bugs we write in
our high-level code or our bugs and are
very visible in the high-level code
matters right in lower level courses
when you talk about performance and you
talk about algorithms you don't worry a
lot about how big things are right in
fact the model for amortized analysis
right is for N greater than and not
right for some problem really large that
analysis is very useful compellingly
important in many cases but in many
cases the question we're trying to
answer isn't how can I solve this
problem with the infinite resources for
the largest possible case it's how can I
solve the problem I need to solve which
is maybe a big with a set of resources
that may be exactly big enough so we
actually need to manage memory think
about it and you know one doesn't want
to have a rich banker right if your
banker is rich what does that mean
you're not right whose money is the
banker spending yours right well we
don't want a rich memory manager we
don't want a memory manager that's using
all of our memory doing right you don't
want a slow memory management want using
all of our time so we're gonna look at
how we can manage memory that's in it in
a way that's efficient both in terms of
space and time
you guys are programmed and see enough
to run into pointer problems out of
balance problems freeing things that
shouldn't be free problems at the end of
the day right the bugs that exist turn
out to be very painful and people pretty
lequip to find them because we're
thinking about the problem we're trying
to solve we're thinking about the
process we need to go through to solve
that problem we're thinking about the
resources we need to use to solve that
problem we're not necessarily thinking
at every juncture about the details of
addresses pointers sizes what starts at
zero and what starts at 1
and so those bugs can be painful memory
performance isn't uniform in many of our
classes we just say look it's in memory
memory is fast or it's in disk and disk
is slow but as it turns out there's a
whole memory hierarchy there are
registers that operate at the speed of
the processor
level one cache that's extremely fast
little two cache that's still pretty
fast
memory that's slow and discs that slow
as molasses in the winter
nevermind remote storage that's probably
twice as low as that it's got to go over
a network first depends on the network
of course ok so we start to think about
how it is that we can organize things in
memory to try to help things float to
the top faster levels so more of what we
use is up here and less of what we use
is in the molasses layers make sense
this is a memory referencing bugs
example if you want to know what a
memory bug looks like you can take a
look at it I don't want to spend a lot
of time looking at it now because we've
got a whole section talking about it and
I think you guys have probably
experienced plenty of memory bugs in
life but the answer is like in most
situations where you have these terrible
errors right the actual output of this
code will be different depending upon
the environment will be depending upon
exactly where it's executing and that
can make it hard to find a problem ok
unlike java python most higher-level
languages there's no intrinsic memory
protection in C it's possible that at
one point in your C program you
overwrite a variable and your program
continues to execute for milliseconds
seconds minutes hours days months years
decades you may wait around forever to
find out that the answer to you know to
the question of life and everything is
43 for those who didn't get that it's
obviously 42
okay why because you corrupted memory at
one point in life and didn't go back to
look at the memory you corrupted until
later
that's a terrible error can you imagine
trying to debug an error that happened
seventy years ago right
in fact when I'm programming on the
extremely rare I mean it happens like
once every 30 years in the extremely
rare case that I make a mistake and that
mistake was a memory error I thank God
for seg faults in fact what anybody who
doubts
I think seg faults or what hundreds of
percent positive proof more so than gaps
in the fossil record that in fact God
does exist and loves you every time I
get a segfault I say thank God God loves
me why because when I get a segfault my
program stops and says you have a
problem and it's right here at this
memory address okay that's great that's
a lot better than discovering that
problem 70 years later not knowing where
it is when I get the wrong answer
inexperienced programmers curse at seg
faults experienced programmers know they
got really lucky and now they know where
to start looking and I don't care about
your religion you can believe that God
loves you not it's fine
okay so she doesn't have the memory
protections of these higher-level
languages so we have to deal with that
we have to deal with the fact that we
may get a seg fault
or even worse we may not and our
programs may just keep running very
painful there's more performance than
asymptotic complexity you remember in
122 and 210 and whatever you know
sophomore level data structures course
you happen to take you were talking
about algorithms analysis and they said
we always do is this thing called Big O
it's type of asymptotic analysis when
you look at what happens when the
problems become really really big
because you cares about dinky little
small problems anyway and we care about
the shape of the curve because
eventually that becomes controlling what
is eventually for something greater than
and not great okay talk about the
analysis some more and they say we throw
away the constant because it doesn't
control the shape of the curve it may
control its dilation but doesn't control
the shape forget the constant we care
about the end behavior cool but I'll
tell you this much as an end user I care
if something takes one second or ten
thousand seconds right
sometimes that constant actually matters
why don't you use the Kasden phone
instead of the samsung phone of the
iphone i or the iphone you know look it
has essentially the same feature set but
the Kasden phone runs 10,000 times
slower let's start up instead of taking
one second after you enter your password
it'll take 10,000 seconds and when you
tap an icon instead of happening in a
millisecond it'll take a second
no one wouldn't use that phone right who
would use that phone no one right in the
real world those constants matter and in
the real world sometimes really small
things make a difference for reasons
we'll talk about later in the semester
if you look at these loops and you see I
and J and J and I you'll find that the
two loops
right those nested loops are in a
different order there one's ji ones I J
I nested within j vs J nested within I
okay in this case right one version is
21 times slower at least on the Pentium
4 why we'll talk about that when we get
there but it has to do with that memory
hierarchy we talked about and using
things that are the faster parts of it
okay
computers do more than execute programs
well one of the important things that
we've got to think about it's ignored
many of the intro classes right is that
you've got to feed the beast if a
computer is doing data processing you
have to get the data in right this is
true for traditional data processing
it's true for you know big data
applications it's true for network
applications somehow right programs need
to process inputs it's only so much fun
to compute the digits of pi right at a
certain point computers want to solve
real world problems with real world data
so input is very important output is
also really important sometimes you want
the computer to processor to be able to
control the machine to do things the
output of a program right is actually
changing something about the device
making a phone ring turning a light on
right sometimes it's sending the data
somewhere else
to disk to an SSD card over a network to
someone else right but unless we have
inputs we can't react to the real world
unless we have outputs we can't affect
the real world
io is really important the role within
our curriculum to thirteen five thirteen
is critically important for a huge
number of classes at the end of the day
any of the classes in CS or ECE that
function that required
building things in software require 2:13
it's really that simple
that's not all there is to computer
science ok
there's a lot of theory that doesn't
require 2:13 that's not all there is to
engineering
ok there are a lot of aspects of
engineering that are very mathematical
ok or don't build things in software
will model them with software all right
but for a year's number of courses 2:13
is a prerequisite and this is only a
subset this doesn't include things like
the graphics classes and the animation
classes and and and and and ok 2:13 when
this course was first developed was
really revolutionary in computer science
education all the courses that tried to
do the same thing for year after year
after year for really decade after
decade were system centric ok
they were classes about the machine for
people that would build the machine
right 213 is different because it's a
course about these systems for the
people that program these systems and
that's a really different perspective
we're not writing the assembly we're
reading it we're not building the memory
controller we're optimizing for it does
that make sense
ok so we'll talk about hardware issues
computer architecture operating systems
compilers networking and so on
io subsystems but we're not going to
look at them in the perspective of those
no take notes dictionary will be
available later or raise your hand which
term cash ok
see ACH e as opposed to see a sh cash I
mean cash like money is good too but but
cash in this case the literal definition
is something like a safe place to hide
things
like an arm's cash like the military is
gonna store a cache of guns somewhere in
case they need them later okay
but in the context of computer systems
it's fat it's a it's a it's a it's a
fast access layer that's smaller than a
larger slower access later so your
browser is a cache of pages you recently
looked at so you can go back and look at
them more quickly the you know the
memory hierarchy has a small amount of
really really fast memory so the things
that you use very frequently you don't
have to get at a slower memory that
answer question excellent okay so you
know there are a whole bunch of
different types of systems and we have
courses in all these areas right we have
a computer architecture course an
operating systems course I compiled of
course the networking course and abed
systems course right we of course is not
in you know in in storage systems and so
on those are for the people building
these things this course covers a slice
of all of that material for the people
using them okay the really serious
programmers okay our goal is to bring
out the hidden hacker and everyone and
we believe that there's a hacker and
everyone you and you and you and you and
even you look excited about your inner
hacker we're gonna find that hacker and
when we do he's gonna be excited I'm
promising we need a front camera so we
can zoom in on people everybody here but
me is missing the excitement on his face
how about you turn around show everyone
your excitement I want them to miss see
that give him a turn around for just
second okay hold that pose while the
camera zooms you got them excellent
okay power programmers manage the flow
of data right you can't have processing
any faster than you can feed the beast
you've got to manage concurrency
concurrency is really really really
really really important right it used to
be the computer had the processor okay
now my cell phone has multiple cores
right your desktop has multiple cores
sometimes you take advantage of multiple
cores just by multitasking having you
Instant Messenger running on one your
operating system on another your word
processor on another and your browsers
run another that doesn't really take
application layer program but sometimes
you have something you want to
accomplish and you want to accomplish it
quickly so you want to take all of that
processing power and use it to attack
the same task rather than dividing it up
among tasks and that gets tricky right
the old saying about too many cooks in
the kitchen right if I have one cook in
the kitchen with one sink in one oven
right one countertop it might take 10
minutes to do something if I have two
cooks in the kitchen
I can't accomplish the same thing twice
in 20 minutes necessarily right if I
want to bake a cake and bacon cake takes
45 minutes if I have one cook it might
you know takes that 45 minutes right if
I put another cook into the kitchen I'm
not gonna end up with two cakes and 45
minutes in fact if they both put flour
into the same Bowl I may end up with no
cakes right if one of them turns the
oven on right two cakes may go in and
then the first one in turns the oven off
the second cake never gets finished
there's a lot of opportunity for
concurrency control problems right maybe
there's only one you know one mixer and
now either somebody needs to way eat or
there's gonna be a fight one Baker will
live
the other fought the good fight okay the
teaching staff perfect myself seth
goldstein friends Franchetti so the
three of us in the faculty you care
about us I mean we're there to help you
and we also have have up like a dozen
dozen and a half TAS I think we've hired
a dozen so far I think we let 150 people
off the waitlist yesterday so I think
we're hiring another six something like
that so I think I think technically
speaking there's 13 today there will be
18 by the end of the week the TAS are
tremendous tremendous you will love them
because they'll hold all these office
hours and the TAS hold office hours like
for several hours a day you know six
days a week
faculty members move a few office hours
with the TAS have many many more why
there are a lot more of them than there
are us they'll answer questions on your
yun you know on your email like we will
- right but if you mail mail the staff
list all of the TAS get the email as
well as all the faculty right so if
there are 18 TAS and three of us there's
six times as likely to answer than we
are right it's great so we're part of it
but the the TAS or another part of it so
15 to 13 verses eighteen to thirteen -
thirteen eighteen to thirteen of based
on the only undergraduates five thirteen
of masters students - thirteen you know
gets live lectures and recitations five
thirteen basically is gonna be delivered
by video the thought there is that
masters students you know having more
experience more time more time
management are able to you know watch
the video on their own time and get the
value out of it
whereas experience has shown that
undergraduates need a little more
structure we're gonna style grade into
thirteen but not in five thirteen and
the reason there is just that we think
we need to provide that input to
undergraduates who are earlier in their
careers but graduate students who either
program you know programmed as
undergraduates and gotten that feedback
already or programmed in industry to
even if his engineers just need that
feedback a little less
everything else is the same the TA isn't
the same the faculty is the same the
lecture materials content the same the
labs are the same blah blah blah blah
blah textbook the revolutionary Brian
did O'Halloran book okay
I say revolutionary because it really
was it was the first book that took this
programmer centered view of systems for
the sophomore level courses been adopted
by all the top universities in the globe
basically what's really cool about it is
Randy actually is a faculty member here
he was our Dean until until until July
and Dave O'Halloran is also a faculty
member here now let me suggest that you
actually legitimately buy the book as
opposed to ripping a copy from I don't
know one of those random sites why you
asked did you legitimately buy the copy
of the book instead of Ripa PDF from
somewhere so here's I'd like to ask you
to do either by a legitimate copy of the
book or go visit Dave in his office with
your PDF copy and say hi Dave I have a
question for you about two-thirty no
cool because he loves to thirteen and
then plop down your laptop with it with
a textbook to answer your question BOC
steam coming out of his ears because it
takes a huge amount of effort right to
prayer and publish the textbook a huge
amount he's here I have my office down
the hall from him he's here to like 2:00
or 3:00 in the morning right you know
like every couple of years for like six
months revising it and apparently when
you publish a textbook so I'm told the
textbook company keeps most of the money
and like the people who write it get
like you know pennies on the you know
like a couple dollars per book or
something right but when you like rip
the PDF copy they get nothing and so he
actually is here and I can attest to it
right until 2:00 or 3:00 in the morning
like for six months every couple of
years it's this huge investment so it
didn't really is cheating him and Randi
if you don't actually buy the book the
course components there are the lectures
these are great my favorite part
then my favorite part is only part they
let me do anymore I can't take that one
let me do the latter dental apps the
recitations the recitations are really
good because their problem sessions okay
I tend to talk about the things are
important
my job right I I believe my job is
somebody lecturing is to communicate to
you what you need to learn right and why
you need to learn it and something about
how to go about learning it and if you
leave lecture knowing those three things
knowing what you need to learn motivated
to learn it understanding why it's
important why you should learn it and
knowing how to go about learning it I've
been successful in lecture I don't think
you can you can absorb all of 15 to 13
in the I don't know what it is you know
we have 15 weeks now and a half we've in
three hours a week 45 hours of lecture
she's not possible okay what you can do
is learn what you need to learn learn
why it's important and how to go about
learning it I think that's why lecture
is important and then you can go right
and you can start reading your textbook
you can start doing your labs doing the
problems and then you can actually learn
okay and so lectures are important
because they help you understand what
you need to learn why you need to learn
it and how to go about learning it's
recitations are really important because
it's an example it's it's a great forum
for seeing examples okay what's an
important part of learning the labs are
critically important and perhaps the
most important parts but you shouldn't
get your finger nails just dug in right
that's what real learning happens right
the rubber reads the meets the road it
actually gets your fingers I didn't
start to do things okay and studying for
the exams the midterm and final is also
a critical part of the course because in
studying for those exams they're problem
oriented exams you'll get a lot of
experience solving very interesting
problems and you're gonna learn a lot so
I think it all works together and now
right now I'm gonna give you right and
our studio audience
and our distance audience the secret to
getting perfect scores on the exam okay
on the course website we have published
like every exam problem we gave from
like 1999 through a couple years ago
okay so here is what you should do in
the next couple of days go and print
every exam we gave in the last five
years every midterm and every final
print them out and then take the last
two or three semesters that we have and
just sit them aside hole okay the most
recent two or three midterms the most
recent two or three finals that are up
on the website take the rest and sort
them by problem type you'll see the
problems tend to fall into a few
different categories of problems and
just make a stack okay integer problems
floating point problems simple assembly
problems struct problems okay
virtual memory problems process control
problems concurrency control problems
okay make several piles and then when we
come to lecture we're going to tell you
all about things right
we'll have electron integers a couple of
lectures on floating point numbers blah
blah blah blah blah so here's what you
do after lecture review your notes read
The Associated part of your textbook and
then go straight for that pile of
problems and start doing them check your
answers the answers are there to do them
until they're boring not because you're
tired but because they're all easy get
help if you need them if there's some
you can't get help you can't figure out
talk to your friends friends are great
okay that doesn't work come to office
hours mind or the TAS or sets or you
know you know whatever right come to the
faculty office hours come to this to
this to the TA office hours email the
course list
right email was great you'll get an
answer if you say hey right now I'm
having trouble with this alright do that
every class don't let yourself get more
than a class behind ever okay try to do
Tuesday Tuesday night or Wednesday try
to do Thursday Thursday night or Friday
if you fall behind get caught up over
the weekend or Monday but don't go into
Tuesday not being caught up if you do
that you're basically guaranteed to get
an a on the exam nothing here is so
complicated that the that anybody who
gets into Carnegie Mellon can't do okay
nothing some people will find it easier
than others that's okay it'll take more
some people you know more or less time
to learn than others that's okay too if
you keep up as you go along everyone
here can get an A it's really that
simple okay can you stop texting don't
text put your phone away
okay so that's the secret then about two
weeks before the midterm you remember I
told you to set about three exams aside
take one whole exam from start to finish
give yourself an hour and a half to two
hours to do it see how you do if
anything was uncomfortable to you or if
you missed anything go back to your pile
of exam problems and drive down again
until you're comfortable then go back
and take another exam repeat is
necessary you'll be getting a hundreds
on the exam I think before you get them
three practice exams that way if not go
to your pile of exams and make yourself
a new exam one problem Adam you know one
problem a one problem B you want problem
C one problem do you one problem a
staple there you go there's a new
practice exam repeat until you got it
when it comes to the final do the same
thing okay
that's the secret somewhere in the
syllabus I think it still has the
language that says to prepare for the
exam read the textbook three times I
mean do that if you want that was
written by the person who wrote the
textbook
but my feeling is dive into the problems
okay
read the textbook as you go right
reading the textbook if you're confused
and miss a problem it's a great resource
but when it comes to the two weeks
before an exam I wouldn't dive right
back to the textbook I would dive to
your you know to your problems do them
as you go review your notes read the
section the textbook do the problems
until they're boring do that all
semester it'll probably take you three
hours to do that right twice a week
maybe four probably three okay but then
when you get to the midterm you're ready
you'll take two midterms three hours of
work and you're ready for the midterm
exam no stress no fuss no mess full
confidence does that make sense okay
getting help the course webpage is a
bunch of resources including the
including the lectures the exams the
assignments and so on we don't use
blackboard for the course except for the
fact that it's used to authenticate
access to the videos so if you were
enrolled in fifteen five thirteen you
have access to the videos I do not
believe at this point in time we're
going to make them accessible to the to
thirteen students we're going to talk
about that the staff meeting we have on
Thursday okay we won't be using Piazza I
get asked a lot why don't you use Piazza
okay
the reason I don't use Piazza is I don't
think it improves learning period okay
that is the singular reason I don't
believe in using Piazza and here's why
okay when you guys go to do labs
you're gonna start writing the lab
you're gonna run into some problem
you're gonna try to push and push and
push and eventually you'll figure out
what the problem is and try to solve it
occasional you'll get stuck and email
the staff list and we'll figure out
where you are and give you some hints
and help you get unstuck so you as
students are gonna have to learn to find
the property notice out you know to
solve a bigger problem define the small
stumbling blocks and to push at them and
to ask questions about it what happens
with Piazza as nearly as I can tell is
the first cohort of students to start
and move the fastest run into all the
interesting cases they asked about them
in on the bulletin boards they get
answers and then what happens is
everybody following behind them doesn't
have the opportunity to think about it
they've already been predisposed to know
where the problems are and predisposed
to know about the solutions and now
they're not learning the problem solving
they're not learning the issue spotting
they're not learning to think about I
have a problem and I have tools which
tools the right one to use for the
problem they're told when you get here
use this tool when you get here use this
tool they're getting a much cheaper
experience and so yes it does
dramatically decrease the number of
questions that are asked on the staff
list view Piazza it does decrease the
number of times you have to answer the
same question will answer the same
question sometimes 80 times on the staff
list it's unusual for it to be that many
but it could happen occasionally does
more often than not whence the same
question in the class this size five to
a dozen times and you know what that's
okay I am happy to answer your question
when you ask it and give you the answer
that's right for you and answer your
question when you ask it and give you
the answer that's right for you and to
give everybody the right answer to the
right question that most importantly at
the right time so my goal in avoiding
Piazza is to ensure that students learn
as much as possible period right even if
that means that we answer more questions
on the mailing list even if that means
we answer questions repetitively on the
mailing list when we see that we're
getting asked questions repair of the
mailing list we have a choice right we
can say this is great these people
running into this interesting probably
want them to some of them we encourage
some of them we help whatever or Wiggins
you know what we should have really
explained that better we now know that
eighty people are confused about it and
now we can improve the course as opposed
to on Piazza where the first person runs
into it we answered everybody else
season we have no idea common that is so
that's my story on Piazza I'm sticking
to it
getting help the fastest thing to do for
help is send an email to the staff list
why somewhere between 13 and 18 people
plus three faculties of sixteen to
twenty one people are gonna be
monitoring that list it's much better
than mailing just me because well I'm in
here teaching this class right now or my
other class at 1:30 or and staff means
at 4:30 right some TA is answering
questions on that list right when I'm up
until 3:00 a.m. I'm answering questions
that list where the early risers on
staff probably starts answering
questions at 7:30 in the morning right
it's just a whole bunch more opportunity
office hours will be starting on this
Sunday they can run Sunday Monday
Tuesday Wednesday and Thursday not on
Friday or Saturday because no one comes
we're gonna go from 6:30 to 8:00 p.m.
and we're still talking about what room
is gonna be held in so give us a couple
more days on that we'll know that on
Thursday afternoon you know we're gonna
talk about it turning our staff meeting
um if you really need a one-on-one
appointment then feel free to request
one in general it's best just to show up
at office hours because you know a
you'll get your question answered be you
can sort of be part of a discussion that
may involve others and some of their
questions may be interesting to you too
you're also likely to find office hours
you know from 6 to 8 p.m. which is
really easy to get there and one-on-one
appointments may take a day or two to
schedule work groups so you must work a
lot on assignments your assignments are
to be done individually ok don't work on
teams bla bla bla bla bla but study
groups are great for doing the practice
problems they are fantastic
right order some pizza get together with
three or four friends do five or six
problems you'll have a good time of more
fun than doing it by yourself when
somebody has a different approach to a
problem than you do you'll get to see
that too if you get stuck on a problem
somebody else will be able to explain it
to you
and vice-versa it'll be great hand ins
are generally due at midnight 11:59 p.m.
so if we say it's due Tuesday it's due
before Wednesday right 11:59 59 you know
p.m. on Tuesday if there's some
irreducible conflict let us know there's
not going to be because we're gonna do
electronic exams this semester and so
you'll be able to schedule the time slot
of your own choosing so there shouldn't
be any of those conflicts if there's a
problem rating please let us know within
a week do it in writing that way we
don't lose track about it we can talk
about it at the staff meeting if you ask
one of us in the hallway we don't have
the opportunity to chat about it at the
staff meeting right because like we're
never gonna remember the syllabus has a
detailed procedure basically it says you
know tell us what the problem is slided
under one of the faculty members doors
you know in terms of computing resources
we can use the machines donated by Intel
short Dell ICS that CSF Samhita edu or a
UNIX dot Andrew either work you get five
great stays this semester the last
assignment is due in the last
assignments due you can't use any great
stays there the reason for that is we
want to make sure that people don't push
that assignment late and then get
stressed out for finals at certain point
it's better just to draw the line turn
it in sync point write lateness penalty
after you use your grace days order the
limit of two grade stays per lab there's
a 15% penalty per day no hand ins after
three days so the most late you can be
on an assignment is three days late the
reason for that is to make sure that you
have enough time to do the next
assignment right comes to that sync
point thing
in the event something really bad
happens a major illness death and family
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah this lateness
penalty stuff is obviously not the right
answer for that right that stuff that
affects you across all of your courses
go talk to your academic advisor explain
to your academic advisor what's happened
where you sit in your classes and put
together a plan to get caught up and
then your academic advisor will email us
and say hey you know this person you
know this person you know needs you to
do this for them okay and then we will
if your academic advisor says give you
you know ten extra days that's fine your
academic advisor says they get caught up
over spring break that's fine whatever
it is we don't care right as long as we
know you've chatted with your academic
advisor and it's gonna be part of a good
solution for you
we're okay with it big advice we have is
once you start getting behind it's
really hard to get caught up right
because to get caught up you'll be able
to maintain the normal course pace plus
the catch-up stuff right that's much
harder than just keeping pace so start
early is our general advice work hard
finish early all that good stuff okay
look don't cheat here's what we know
okay we know that this is perhaps the
best-selling textbook for this course
anywhere in the world we know this set
of labs that come with a textbook right
is perhaps the most popular set of labs
for this course anywhere in the world we
know that students all over the world
have posted answers to these labs in any
number of forums okay Dave O'Halloran
has made it his life's mission to find
every one of these and add them to our
database of solutions that we use when
we run mas okay it's run automatically
by Auto lab every time you turn in a
solution okay
Auto lab has it and then at the end of
the lab moss is run and gives the report
of what solutions match each other and
what solutions match the ones Dave is
put in there
okay now I'm the one who follows up on
those I can assure you I follow up on
every one of those but those of you who
know me know there's an expression on
campus
it's called Kasdan time five minutes
late ish okay I don't necessarily follow
up on those immediately so if you turn
in a solution to a lab and it's copied
it's not like red lights are going to
flash and bells are going to ring all at
once if you do that for three labs in a
row I may not notice until I get around
to looking at the mas results the last
couple of weeks of the semester but I do
we prosecuted 20-some odd cases of
cheating last semester
two students were thrown out of the
University
one more is a hearing come up coming up
to discuss the same don't cheat it's
really serious okay
I mean in one case you know I submitted
the report that you know within days of
another instructor submitting a report
that student got thrown out in two other
cases it was a second offense that you
know in another case we don't know the
outcome of this one I don't think yet it
was somebody who cheated twice in 213 a
year apart
just don't weaken google - okay my
personal favorite cave I have several
personal favorite cases one of my
personal favorite cases if somebody was
at a Google dinner a Google intern
dinner okay
bragging about how she did all of her
labs all the labs from her boyfriend who
is a Stanford student great well who
else is sitting around the table at a
Google intern dinner do you think right
a bunch of - 13 TAS who happen to be
Google interns or at least were at some
point in their career
okay so I don't remember whether it's
actually a Google intern or one of the
Google mentors but it took like six
seconds from the dinner table right for
somebody to tap the text both me and the
instructor at Stanford that person got
bust both of them got busted right don't
I just I don't know I don't know how it
is that we managed to bust anybody
during the semester because you know
what we do we have all of your solutions
in auto lab we run moss against them and
if you think that Stanford and CMU and
Berkeley and MIT you know and Cornell
and so on are very far apart take a look
at our faculties and realize that we're
all alums from other places right our
students mix right you know it's just
not gonna work for you my other personal
favorite was the case where a student
cheated the code exactly matched
something from github that Dave
O'Halloran found and put it in the
database thanks Dave
this that I call a student in my office
the student immediately starts
confessing which is good I mean that's
actually the right way for this to
happen right but the problem is the
students confession didn't match what I
was looking at I was looking at the
students code and github code
and they were exactly the same and the
student was confessing to getting too
much help the student said I am so so
sorry I know I shouldn't have done it I
was having a whole bunch of trouble with
the course that was really struggling
and my my father decided that he needed
to hire me a teacher to help me and so
he got me this teacher and I got too
much help from this teacher and I know
what I know I shouldn't have gotten that
much help and I said well that's really
interesting and he said no no I'm so
sorry the guy's practically in tears
confessing to getting too much help from
this teacher I said but the problem here
is that your lab matches github
I don't nothing about this teacher he
says no it can't
yes yes it does dear and so apparently
his father hired him this faculty member
at the University of Outer Mongolia I'm
not making that up some some teacher
Peng and there's some Chinese equivalent
of Skype and so he Skyped with this
person in China who helped him with his
lab and apparently the way this guy
helped him was by feeding him lines
three lines at a time from github so as
nearly as I can tell neither the student
nor teacher Peng could do the lab so
this poor person's father paid this
teacher in China to rip code from github
and feed it to him over some Chinese
skype like service um don't cheat we
will catch you we will really honestly
truly it's not there it's not like work
it's just is not hard we have a database
of solutions and a tool that compares
them there's a button on the lab panel
that says find cheaters run boss don't
cheat
laptops are admitted of course for
looking at slides you previously
downloaded or taking notes but not for
electronically mediated communication
presidents and lectures is voluntary
take no recordings of any kind will
prove
the videos for the 5:13 crowd exams 20%
for the midterm 30% for the final labs
count half their weight varies the
simpler shorter labs count less than the
longer more involved labs topics
integers floating point arithmetic
assembly language programs how C you
know you know C is represented in
assembly data structures represented
assembly certain aspects of architecture
and compilers the first three labs play
with those topics next topics topics we
cover the memory hierarchy caches disks
spatial and temporal locality and
certain other aspects of how the
operating systems manage these the cache
lab lab 4 covers these Hardware
exceptions processes process control
UNIX signals non-local jumps this is
covered by lab 5 the teach lab will you
write a shell virtual memory address
translation and that mix storage
allocation caching involved there like
the TLB this is tested in the Mallik lab
networking and guernsey control this is
tested in proxy lab ok
the idea behind all these labs the same
give you a well-defined goal some
problem to solve and let you lose to
actually build the solution you'll pick
a handle a name that's not yours nor the
name of you know any faculty member or
TA
[Music]
okay some Elias and it'll rank your
solution on the scoreboard okay and so
at a certain point you get full credit
and everything after that is for
bragging rights okay that way you know
that you can stop at a certain point but
if you really want to keep driving
forward and somebody has a faster mallet
than you well you know it's possible you
can drive forward and try to leapfrog
them if you want Labs are submitted via
the auto lab system basically point at
it and go as of today if you're enrolled
you have an auto lab account if you
don't if you just enrolled more recently
than we added them at 10:00 a.m. we'll
get you your account tomorrow waitlists
if you're trying to get into the 15
section talk to Katherine Fichtner if
you're trying to get into the 18 section
talk to Zahra Cole yay if you're trying
to get into 15 5 13 you should already
be in if not you're not seeing this
video because the video is behind
blackboard which is registration
controlled by the list of people who's
in um don't contact me or the other
instructors we have no control over the
waitlist guys excited yeah I'm excited
have a great day everybody
Subtitles End: mo.dbxdb.com