Youtube subtitles download by mo.dbxdb.com
okay so let's say picking off we left
off last class bits bytes and integers
okay so remember the last pass we talked
about about standards or representation
right reach bit is nothing more than a
binary digit right and if you want to
know what the value is you sum up each
place right you know you know if there's
a 1 we have the value that plays if
there's a 0 we don't and you just sum
across the whole thing and that gives
you the value of the number we talked
about two's complement which was that
really weird notation right where we
complement that every digit we added 1
and this actually sort of made some
sense because if you do that and you add
a number to its complement you get 0 ok
and we talked about why that actually
works the fact that if you had you know
and the fact that it's the way carryout
works that mean that makes that work in
fact if I take 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 and I
add 0 I'm sorry I add 1 I get all zeroes
right
meaning that one more woman 1 right is
the additive complement of inverse of 1
and how we built up two's complement
notation from there right all one's plus
1 is 0 so all one's therefore is
negative 1 ok yeah and we talked about
the fact how in two's complement
notation right we start out with the
most negative number one followed by all
zeros and then we add back to that as we
start to turn other digits on and
actually bring ourselves closer to 0
which is why all 1s is negative 1 the
closest integer to 0 because we've added
everything back right ok it's sort of
important to have an intuition as to why
these things work because it really
makes the 213 exams much easier because
you know we're gonna have an exam you
know question that basically asked you
to play with integer numbers you we have
every single semester right for the last
15 years it probably even longer than
that I've been here since 99 I think
this this tradition started in 98 so you
could try to memorize a whole bunch of
bit patterns or you can just have
intuition as to why it works and say
okay if I add 1 to all ones I'm gonna
get 0 therefore all ones
one great if that's negative one and I
take off a 1 that's negative 2 right and
then work your way back do you have a
one and all zeroes it's the most
negative number right it all sort of
makes sense all right and then we talked
about the fact that in these we need a
way to tell two's complement number from
a number that's not two's complement
right if we don't I mean they're all
they're all numbers which way do I
interpret it so the way we interpret it
is that if the leading digit is a 1 we
interpreters two's complement if the
leading digit is a 0 we interpret it as
a regular number and that tells us how
to interpret our result remember the
adder for you know for a regular
representation the adder for two's
complement and the adder for adding a
regular representation to two's
complement are all the same we do the
same thing it's just a bitwise add
that's what's beautiful about this right
that's actually why we originally
invented these notations because it
means that we only need one adder and a
processor we don't need to have
something that's two tracks right I have
positive numbers with one represent a
you can have negative numbers with
another representation I could add using
my adder and if I want to subtract I
generate a 2's complement than that add
took fewer transistors that way okay all
right and so we talked about the fact
that when were that when we're trying to
take I would say a 16-bit number and
represented as a 32-bit number we have
to do sign extension if it's a two's
complement number we need to take those
ones and move them out right if we don't
it's gonna turn into a into a puttan to
a non negative number if we have a non
negative number we need to take those
zeros and copy them on the way out
otherwise if we put if we start putting
in ones it's gonna turn into a into a
two's complement number right as far as
how we interpret it okay all right so
now let's take a look at unsigned
addition I have two numbers U and V and
I add them together here's the question
if I take two unsigned integers and add
them together
what is
the biggest result that I can have and
let's not worry about exactly the number
right let's ask how many bits if I have
2 4 bit numbers and I add them together
in the worst case how many bits do I
need to represent the result yeah 5 y 5
yeah I mean you're exactly right look
with each binary digit right as I move
from my low order digit my ones bit to
my twos bet to my fours bit to my eights
bit to my 16s bit to my 32 bit to my 64
is bit each bit is worth twice the bit
before it right the 64's bit is worth
twice that the 32 bit twice the 16 bit
twice the 8 bit twice the 4-bit twice
the two bit twice the 1 bit right so if
I add if I if I if I take something and
I add it to itself how big is it yell it
twice twice double right so if I if my
digit is one and I add it to a one
what's the most it can become a - I
can't do any worse than doubling
something right that's it if I double
something I need one more bit by adding
right all ones to all ones the most I'm
gonna need is one more bit and that's
the worst case right the biggest number
I can have in n bits is n ones right I
have a 4-bit number the biggest number I
can have is one one one one if I add
that number to itself it's one plus one
I doubled that fit one plus one I
doubled that bit one plus one I doubled
that bit one plus one I doubled that bit
one plus one I doubled that bit if I
double all the bits I double the number
all I need is one more bits for twice
one more bid for twice as big one two
four eight the next bits gonna be 16
does that make sense now that doesn't
mean I necessarily need an extra bit
right if I have a 4-bit number and I
have you know 1 1 0 0 1 1 0 0 I can add
a 1 and I don't need any more bits I can
add it 1-0 and I don't need any more
bits I can add a 1 1 I don't need any
more bits I only need more bits if I'm
trying to add something that has a 1 in
the first the high order two bits
make sense okay so that's all this slide
here is trying to tell us if I had two
you know two numbers are the same with
the most I need is one extra bit okay
now if I add two 32-bit numbers but most
i need is a 33 bit number unfortunately
right that's not how the world works
right if I have if I have some size for
my data type and it's 32 bits and I need
a 33 bit number I've lost that
high-order bit the way this works is
like modular arithmetic it wraps around
okay so I lose the high-order bit and
keep the low-order bits the high-order
bit it's called carry out just gets
dropped okay so it's modulus arithmetic
it's like we go around the clock and
then we get too high right we lose the
number of times we went around that
clock right and we keep wherever the you
know the hand hex happens to be okay so
that's how it works it just wraps around
now as it turns out when it comes to
mathematical operations we have a carry
out like this we'll learn a little later
that gets stored in a flag so in this
particular case we can actually sort of
figure it out if we try we can see that
our result is whatever our result
happens to be and then we can go back
and look and see that carry flag is on
or not okay
so what is this well I have my two
numbers you being one number WV being
another number right and so this shows
you being 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12
13 14 right
and this shows thee and so if we hold V
constant for a moment at 0 we can just
see this plot that shows you with every
value from 0 to 15 that makes sense
unsurprisingly 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
it goes up monotonically right now if I
say that instead of being 0 V is 1 well
what happens well
I start out a little higher I'm now
starting out at 1 instead of 0 right but
I finish up in the same place basically
right ok
and so basically what we see is given
any combination of U and V I can't get
above in this case 15 make sense okay
and then so that forms a nice planar
surface
all right now what happens if I add two
numbers you know that get me past that
you're the size of my data type well we
see the nice planar surface when you saw
in the prior slide but now what happens
is if we go one past we go from one one
one one right to zero zero zero zero
once we go one pass we crash down to
zero zero zero zero zero and that's what
that line shows when the sum of U plus V
right turns out to be one more than we
can store then what happens right then
it's zero and from that point we just
start growing again if we the sum of U
and V is one more than the point where
it becomes zero well it's one more than
all zeros it's one and that's what that
line is and so on so we form a second
plane if we keep going right we can't
why can't we have a third plane yeah
yeah so we said right if you add two
things together they can't be worse than
double right and so here's the single
there's the double you can't get a third
plane out of that because if I add two
numbers at worst case they're double
what they were before make sense
everybody seen this view on it all right
two's complement addition well two's
complement addition is exactly the same
right as normal addition we showed this
right we took a regular number right and
added it to a two's complement number
and got zero using a regular adder and
then we showed that if we added one to
that right whether we added that one to
the two the two's complement number
added that one to the other number right
it grew by one and so on that's the
beauty of this is it allows us to do
addition and subtraction with just an
adder right the way math works is
exactly the same it's just the way that
we interpret the numbers that changes
the bits are the same they're still bits
in a number the operation the adder is
still the same it's still adding 1 and 1
to get 0 and carry a 1 we're warning 0
to 1 ok so there's really no difference
alright how we interpret things however
might be slightly different
oK we've been through that before let's
get to the picture now you see in effect
we have the same two planes we had
before we have one plane here and one
plane here to see that we've got to pick
this piece up and move it over here not
surprising right because it's the same
math we had before we're just
interpreting it differently it's the
same bits added by the same adder we're
just choosing to renumber the number
line ok to change where 0 is which
shifts where these planes are do you see
that it's still the same number line
right if you go back to third grade or
first grade and have that number line
you used to learn adding it's still the
same number line with the same line line
line line line line line line ok if you
add 4 you're still moving forward by 4
if you add 2 you're still moving forward
by
- okay in this case if you get to the
end you just loop back to the beginning
it works just the same and it works just
the same as your first grade number line
whether you're using two's complement
numbers or regular numbers the only
difference is what labels we put on
those points so what happens when you
add negative 1 to negative 1 so right so
if I add negative 1 to negative 1 I have
a carry out situation right and you know
really the problem there is if you look
at the number line what you find is that
there is we like to think of it as
positive numbers and negative numbers
but the reality of the situation is that
there are negative numbers and
non-negative numbers and 0 is a non
negative number which comes out of the
non negative side of the number line the
result of that is that we do have one
more on the negative side than we do on
the non negative side so our most
negative number is not balanced by is
not equal to the most positive number
it's one less and so you know how do I
explain that it's an edge case but
that's the reason that there's the edge
case it's not some random math is broken
it's we have this artifact okay and so
there you have it
right the same two planes we had before
but they're slightly different right in
that this starts out with the most
negative number right this ends with the
most positive number if you add the two
most negative numbers together you're
obviously not going to get 0 we're two
very negative numbers together you're
not going to get 0 right ok and you were
talking before you're talking about the
case of of the of the value 1 in all
zeroes right
who-who's question was that you were
asking about one or all zeros right or
ones okay all ones not one I'm sorry
so all ones up well what were you
talking about I was confused actually
another thing about your question I'm
actually slightly confused okay so if I
do negative one and negative one right
so if I add all ones and all ones what
do I end up with the bit pattern for for
negative ones what Oh once okay and so
if I add if I add all ones I'm sorry I
misinterpreted your question so if I add
if I add all one stall ones what am I
actually gonna get go ahead are you
happy yeah you sure yeah okay I thought
you'd ask me the question we the
high-order bit was up where was with the
I thought you're asking different
questions I apologize so the the problem
the the problem the problem is that T is
the T min plus t max doesn't equal zero
okay that's where the system we have
breaks down a little bit B is the number
one isn't symmetric and so if you take
the absolute value of T min you end up
with a slight mess does that make sense
that's where that's where the system
breaks down but you're okay with
negative 1 plus negative 1 yeah okay
so if I have the most if we forget about
the symbols for a moment I take the
biggest negative number the negative
number I have with the greatest
magnitude and I add it to the positive
magnitude the result is not going to be
zero what's that
yes it's gonna be minus one does that
make sense so it's not the case if I
take the absolute value of T min then
I'm gonna get what I think I'm gonna get
because there is no absolute value of T
men that make sense
there's just no there's we don't have
that point on our number line okay so
back to this so this shows basically the
same two planes we had before but our
number line has now been remembered
instead of our number line you know
going from going from zero here right on
up right it's starting here at negatives
and so it's just been shifted but the
basic thing is it's still the same we
still keep adding right until the point
where all of our bits become one and we
add one and it rotates back to zero it
doesn't matter that's now happening from
a negative number versus from a positive
number right
I can under flow just as well as I can
under overflow and that's always the
case if you take if you take zero and
subtract one right you're gonna end up
wrapping forward to a big number so this
is nothing more than a renumber align it
doesn't change the math the planes are
still the same we've just moved them by
starting zero somewhere different yes
okay go ahead
actually you actually get all the ones
carryover it still ends up being like
just do it but you do get so rebase his
answer was basically says was if you
concerned about negative 1 plus negative
1 do it yeah
actually write it out on your paper
right now and you'll see that it
actually works if you're concerned about
negative team min and team in not being
balanced you're correct and they're
simply not yes see it again so okay so
the question is if we have a bit pattern
with T min what does that bit pattern
look like what is the bit pattern 14 min
that's all I care about right now 1
followed by all zeros that one is in the
highest order position right so if I
take ones in the highest order position
and I add them together that position
becomes what 1 plus 1 becomes 0 and that
one gets carried out right because 1 + 1
is 2 right 0 in the current place and 1
in the next place over does that make
sense so if I have a bit my 1 + 1 or the
highest bit that bit becomes 0 carry the
1 and there's nothing there to carry it
to so I just have all zeros does that
make sense
does that answer your question
that was a very tentative yes
see Europe set their brakes the Europe
said there could break well so what I
can tell you is that is the behavior and
the question is is that behavior
intuitive to people the answer is no
which brings us back to the discussion
we had the thirty first day of class
which is why 213 is a critical class
because in our everyday lives as
programmers we forget these things and
we write a lot of software that assumes
that an INT is an integer and then
sometimes we get these edge cases and
they matter right and if we're writing
software that can tolerate some failure
maybe we discover this in advance and
then we have to go back and fix a bug
not the best of all worlds if writing
isn't mission critical software we're
mission critical is you know you allow
that you apply your your definition
there but we're we can't tolerate bugs
which is a lot of software really you
have to think of these things in advance
right and ensure that your data is in
proper ranges that your data is properly
normalized or that you use a library an
arbitrary precision arithmetic library
that can stack integers together to give
you a bigger one
obviously in software not in hardware
does that address your question okay I
saw some other hands popping up yes so
right so this is the question is where
does this system originate okay well
first of all this class is x86 based and
this is the system used by the x86
family of processors okay secondly for
historical reasons this is the system
used by any general-purpose processor on
earth at this point the reason signed
over fluency is undefined is because the
the the inventors and standard keepers
for C do not want to impose a standard
in the language that is not necessarily
going to be supported by the underlying
architecture and they're confident that
the
underlying architecture will be able to
add stuff in the middle they're not
confident about what the underlying
architecture might do when the
representation breaks down and so if
they would have said see must work this
way and then somebody would have
invented a simpler processor for a
simpler application right we're simple
was the rule day now math gets really
complicated if they want to try to use C
on so that's why the folks who design C
basically said you know here's the
number line you good as long as you stay
on the number line if you cross this
edge across this edge
you better know what's going on
underneath because we're giving you no
promises the architecture may give you
promises the compiler writer may give
you promises right good or bad luck may
give you something but we as the C
language are gonna are not gonna give
you an answer to that question I saw
some other hands somewhere here
somewhere anywhere nope okay
ah there are a lot of words on that
slide some of them are boldface I see
time signs it's always bad even worse
they're they're like exponents lease
there are no subscripts I really hate
what I have exponents add subscripts
there's one oh shit oh no oh no just
kidding
alright so now let's talk about
multiplication multiplication is
obviously more complicated than like
addition right you learn addition and
subtraction in kindergarten and
first-grade didn't get the
multiplication till second or third okay
so let me ask you this we said that if I
add two numbers together the worst case
that the number is doubled what if I
multiply two numbers together let's
imagine we multiply two two bit numbers
together how big could my result be well
what's the biggest two-bit number
what's the bit pattern for the biggest
two-bit number one one one one
represents what decimal number I waiting
for somebody say that so we're playing
with unsigned numbers it represents the
rate otherwise negative one okay
so let's assume we're dealing with out
in sign for the moment so the the worst
case four integer multiplication is
going to be for two bit into
multiplications three times three which
is what nine we agree if I need to
represent nine in binary how many digits
does it take me four right 1 2 4 right 4
plus 2 is 6 plus 1 is 7 not there right
1 2 4 8 right so we have an 8 plus no 4
is plus no 2's plus a 1 okay
now let's play with a 3 bit number if I
have a 3 bit unsigned number what's the
biggest number I can represent 7 4 plus
2 plus 1 if I multiply 7 & 7 what do I
get if I multiply 7 & 7 what do I get
49 how many bits is take to represent 49
1 2 4 8 16 right how many bits to the
take so if I do 1 2 4 8 16 that's 5 bits
that gives me 231 how many bits do I
need 6 okay so I started out with 2 3
but with 2 / 3 bit numbers I needed a
6-bit I needed up to 6 bits for the
result I had to I had booked about 2 2
bit numbers I needed how many bits for
the result how many 4 ok let's try it
one more time let's say we have a 4-bit
number 1 1 1 1 what does that represent
fifteen okay if I multiplied 15 and 15
what do I get
what's that two twenty-five
okay how many bits does it take to
represent 225 1 2 4 8 16 32 64 128 right
so 128 gets me to 255 right how many
bits does it take what's that
1 2 4 8 16 32 64 128 that gets me to 255
right so I multiply 2 4 bit numbers how
many bits did I need a ok so what seems
like the general rule here twice as many
why now give me the intuition beyond
that now we've gone through and play the
game yeah
to the N times 2 to the N is 2 to the 2n
is that what you're suggesting
ok ok so I think you're exactly right so
if you wanna take this as a mathematic
you're exactly right
tuning it you know 2 to the N times to
the N is equal to 2 to the 2n right and
that's twice as many bits because each
bit represents a power of 2 beautiful
that's actually an excellent way of
thinking about it if you happen to be a
mathematician any mathematician can
leave the room for the rest of the
explanation and so for those who aren't
mathematical and they're thinking and
that is an excellent way of thinking
about it right what intuition do we have
yeah we're shifting them
maybe that I think that may complicate
some things to think of it that way so
let's think about it in in when you were
learning multiplication in second or
third grade they told you that
multiplication is repeated addition
right then if I multiply four times two
that's like adding two to itself four
times by multiply three times five
that's like adding three to itself five
times and five to itself three times go
ahead
so I like your thinking I'm not sure the
word amortized applies the suggestion
was that it's like we added multiple
times and each time can cause a carry
but I know I'm gonna have it max with
carries okay so think about it this way
okay if I'm trying to multiply 2w bit
numbers all right you know if I'm trying
to multiply two W bit numbers to three
bit numbers right we said how many extra
bits would it take it can result in six
if I have two 4 bit numbers how many
bits would take a right to 5 bit numbers
how many bits 10 right the reason for
this what's that the reason for this is
that if every time I'm doing one of
those ads right
I could need one more bit and I have to
do that up to that many times of ads I
could need that many more bits right
which brings us right back to your
explanation which is that 2 to the N
times 2 to the N is to the 2n okay so
that's really where the slide is going
okay so of course that's just as
impossible as it was with addition right
I have a fixed word size for my data
type when I get to the edge of that
right something is going to happen I'm
gonna wrap around to 0 just like with
addition it's modular arithmetic okay
so with addition right I could wrap
around at most once right my two
positive numbers being added could
result in a negative number what about
with with multiplication how many times
do I wrap around
you're grabbing at it I can see it okay
so let's take a look has that all right
all right
so unsigned multiplication see we have
you times me the true product can be 2w
time to W times the bits right so gonna
be up to double right
why if I have my full width size i could
need another full width size okay and we
saw that we took three six we said four
eight right that's all that's saying
right here the rest of these get
discarded so we say discarded coming
back to your question how many times
could we end up going around the clock
right that's captured by these numbers
right that's why this is modular
arithmetic we're throwing this away and
just keep and we just keep will we land
up all right so it ignores the high
order bits
okay now what about power of two
multiplied
okay we know that each bit position is
worth double the bit position to its
right we also know that each bit
position is worth half the bit position
to its left right those two go together
so it is true that if I want to multiply
something by two I can left shift it if
I want to divide something by 2 I can
write shift it and this works most of
the time but it does get us into some
weird situations for example if I write
shift 2 divided by 2 what happens if it
was not a number what happens if there
was a 1 in that rightmost bit that one
doesn't become a half right there's no
half in an integer so it gets thrown
away gets discarded in the word of the
slide right so even numbers my right
shift I'm gonna end up with 1/2 odd
numbers my right shift we're gonna
truncate that one to a zero what about
what I left shift well that's gonna work
well for a while but then I get to the
point where I have a 1 in that leftmost
bit right and when I write and my left
shift it falls off the edge modular
arithmetic ok now it is true that in a
processor the left shift and right shift
operations are faster than a multiply
operation a multiply operation is
relatively expensive a lot of logic that
has to happen to do multiply right so
some people who learn this tend to mess
up their code and start converting any
anything where they multiply by a power
of two to a right or left shift don't do
that right don't do that absolutely
don't do that there are two reasons you
should not do that the first reason is
that anybody who has to read your code
is gonna have trouble when you left
shift by 3 because it's not going to be
immediately obvious to them why you did
that
they're not going to immediately say oh
they're left shifting by 3 because they
want to divide by 8 okay they either say
why am i left shifting by 3 like
some people may look at that and go
what's going on with the arrows right
it's an application programmer who
doesn't do bit stuff right somebody else
may look at it and think oh I'm doing
the bitwise shift what is this and this
is obviously not a number and somebody
else will eventually realize that you're
doing that because you're trying to
divide by a power - okay here's the
thing you go ahead and do it divided by
a power of two in this magical piece of
software the compiler will say aha
that's a power of two I'm going to
convert this to a left shift for them
and so if you write your code as normal
you get the benefit of both worlds
readable code and fast code so why do we
talk about this we talk about this
because if you go back for whatever
reason and read the assembly that the
compiler generated for your code or
debug into the assembly that the
compiler generated for your code you may
sometimes see where you had a divided by
a power of two and it replaced it with a
left shift well you had to multiply by a
power of two and it replaced it with the
right shift does that make sense and
that should not mystify you because you
should know that power of two
multiplication division can be
represented as shifts does that make
sense and the compiler will do this for
you okay okay most machines shift in
that fast the multiply the compiler
generates this code for you you don't
write it this way because it makes your
code less readable and gains you nothing
because the compiler will do this for
you having said that when you're looking
at code and see things that are left
shifts and right shifts you should think
left shift and right shift and then you
should think divide and multiply okay
power of two divide if we imagine a
binary point imagine integer
multiplication know binary point we'll
see the problem that I was talking about
before which is that a 1 here gets
shifted off to there some like to say it
gets truncated the reality is it just
goes away all right if we want to fix
that problem what do we do
you guys did it in like you know fourth
grade when you learn rounding well let's
have you don't wanna round down though
okay so if we think about non-negative
numbers if I always add one before I
write shift I'm gonna guarantee that I'm
gonna round up because if it's a zero
and I put a 1 there if it's an even
number already and I add a 1 I've done
nothing to it
that one gets thrown away when I write
shift if however it's an odd number and
I add 1 it's one of one that causes a
carry then when I left shift I'm
dropping a zero so I forced that half to
get rounded up does that make sense
you're allowed to come in you don't just
down at the door you know what to go
away either you're allowed to come in ok
grab a seat make yourself at home
alright so do you see how that works now
let's take a funny case let's take the
case of negative numbers let's say for a
moment that I have a negative number and
I right shift someone tell me what
happens
take out your paper give yourself a
simple negative number and write shifted
a negative number where there's a one in
the rightmost bit all right yeah we're
the medic we don't want to break it
right your hand is up questions yeah we
want to go ahead and order you know a
medic shift so we don't intentionally
break things I want to know which way
this rounding now goes and now people
telling me both up and down so it helps
you actually write it out I know that
you know pencil and paper like
deprecated if you've got a tablet you
can actually use your little stylus and
write on the screen if you're limited to
keyboards you know then that's okay you
can type numbers too that works I don't
get somebody in the back on this one
I've been picking on the front corner
right here
Wow I don't know let's see
I'm Greg
Morgan nice to meet you Morgan so what
do you think was one one zero zero once
what do you think that represents in in
terms of an integer value negative nine
do you guys have brains give me a quick
test one one zero zero one is that
negative nine
perfect
it's like
how many people think it's negative nine
raise your hands
I think it's negative seven raise your
hands yeah so if we look at that one one
zero zero one right the easy way to
think of that is if it was all ones what
would it be negative one but we don't we
have two zeros there right
four and two right so that's six so it's
negative one minus six negative seven
okay so we got a negative seven
all right now what do you think okay so
you're right shifted it by two and so we
lose that rightmost one bit it's now it
becomes four ones one one one one zero
zero now if we take a look at there at
the result there it's one one one one
zero I'm sorry okay so now if we take a
look at that it's the same as all ones
which would be negative one right minus
1 which is negative 2 so which way did
that round when you say down what do you
mean these are two ways of looking at
this there is closer to zero versus
farther from zero and there is down as
in more negative rounds closer to zero
how do you agree that it rounds closer
to zero raise your hands
how many people disagree that it rounds
close to zero raise your hands hmm so
let's take a minute and write it out I'm
just gonna hang out and relax
so this original number represented what
rated out in thing up so this number
that you now have represents what and if
you would have added that one if it so
that so that was okay so that would be
if we did that way that would be
negative three and a half right negative
7/2 would be nominally negative three
and half so right that way thanks to us
looks like everybody else did it first
yes
oh he register before that's fine yeah
so you actually have you do you divide
by 2 or bucks by 4 okay everything I
think I totally bring else into my bike
- so let's do this yeah so now that
becomes where's this actually okay hey
guys that Joy's an inconsistent a year
we should be dividing by we should be
dividing by four because that's what he
said he shifted by two that's divided by
four let's put it back to the example
yeah
[Applause]
and then so what we have this is 7/4 is
water to bed which are the transfers and
decimals we have seven who lead is 7/4
for now good enough and then what's this
so all one's be negative one
there's no one's negative okay what so
this is negative two this is negative
one or something
we draw these on our number line that's
my zero and this is 7/4 right and that's
my negative two right and so which way
to the count so it's more negative it's
more negative we wear down as down as
becomes ambiguous here right so it's
definitely rounded more negative right
which is not necessarily close to zero
as it was before
okay guys what do we think in this case
when we took the the one one zero one
one zero zero one the negative 7/4 right
ideally in our minds this was gonna be
negative 7/4 let's not worry about it
beyond that point we need to break it
down two fractions when we write shifted
that 2/4 right and we write chipped it
away the two might rightmost bits what
did we end up with negative 2 so we
think about that in the number line
right we have negative 7/4 right which
is less than 2 right and then we have
negative 2 so when we rounded which way
did we round we rounded a wafer we
rounded more to the left right and at
one level this is perfectly consistent
right at one level when we were dealing
on the positive side of the number lines
not negative sides a number line and we
rounded which way do we go left now we
rounding the same we rounding on the
other side of the number line but using
the same mathematical rules right which
way do we shift which way is that
there's a rounding go left everybody
agreed
so it's perfectly consistent in terms of
the way meant you'd expect a
mathematical operator to face its
rounding left in either case the problem
is to us humans it's less intuitive
because on the right side of the number
line its rounding down what we mean
towards zero smaller absolute value and
yet on the left side and underlined its
rounding down we're now down means left
or a greater absolute value do you see
the paradox do you see why this math is
just unfriendly to people okay left to
its own devices rounding is always going
to be to the left which means a greater
absolute value for negative numbers and
a smaller absolute value for the
non-negative numbers if that's not the
way we want the rounding to work we need
to fix it in a negative case does that
make sense
or what fix it in the positive case by
adding or subtracting something to make
the math work out our way but it's
naturally intuitively inconsistent to
people because it's always rounding left
rather than rounding towards zero in
both cases which is what we'd want we'd
want you to be able to take a positive
four and a negative four divide you make
a positive five and negative five
divided each by two add them together
and get zero and that's not what the
president math allows because they're
both getting rounded this way so one's
getting a greater absolute value the
negative one and the positive one's
getting a smaller absolute value so when
they're added the negative wins okay and
that's what we're going with that and so
if we want to correct it we need to add
a bias and we talked about that okay
okay
so some basic rules of arithmetic we
were dealing with signed or unsigned
it's normal addition followed by a
truncate and we talked about the
consequences of that unsigned arithmetic
is mod two signed arithmetic is is sort
of mod two
but then it gets weird right
multiplication is basically normal
multiplication followed by a truncate if
it's unsigned as mod 2 if it's signed
it's still like again basically mod 2
but it gets weird because the number
lines has been Rinat has been relabeled
and we saw that we saw the way the plane
shifted why should I use unsigned I'm
gonna skip past that slide for a minute
and the reason I'm gonna skip past that
slides I think it's too simple if you're
using unsigned numbers you get a much
greater range because your number line
starts at 0 and goes forward you're not
shifting it to make it centered about 0
in general this is good if you don't
need negative numbers because now you
can handle bigger numbers which means if
you get bigger inputs than you expect
you'll be able to handle them so a
common type of advice is use unsigned
numbers unless negatives can occur
however I need to warn you that
negatives occurring in the common case
is different than negatives occurring in
a case where something goes wrong so we
say use unsigned and less right you need
negative numbers we mean under any
circumstances you will encounter a
negative number a negative number is bad
input is one case because if somebody
gives you something like negative 5 and
you interpret that as a huge number
that's a problem okay if something goes
wrong with your system that should never
be freezing and now it is it'd be nice
to know that and not turn on the air
conditioner because you think it's too
hot right so we say use unsigned numbers
unless you need negative numbers we mean
you need negative numbers under any set
of circumstances including you being fed
badly does that make sense so it's
critical to ask yourself when choosing
the the data type you need which data
type is giving going to give me the most
robustness giving any data I can
encounter good and bad
and if you can use a larger data type
than you need why who cares if an
integer is a little bit bigger like
whatever if you've got plenty of memory
go with the long instead of an int now
you're safer oK we've got a whole bunch
of the classic c puzzles right and again
i'm gonna leave most of these for you to
play with because i don't think there's
a lot of good that comes out of me doing
puzzles for you what's that okay they're
not okay so at the end of the day we get
some value into X and we get some value
and Y we don't know where they come from
and now we have an unsigned u X and an
unsigned uy okay and now the question is
for each of the following expressions is
a true or false and why sort of like you
to do with these actually do them do
them on your own and if you have
questions get together your friends who
are doing them on my own and talk to
them study groups are amazing tools and
then that if you still have questions
because you and your friends are having
you know or are now wrestling each other
and beating each other up over the
correct answer come to office hours will
pull tables out of the way let you
wrestle for a while and then we'll
declare a winner not based upon who's
the most polite or who gets knocked out
but based upon what actually works and
then you'll have some fun and you'll
have your answers but really give them a
try yourself
okay we know that memory is byte
oriented this shouldn't shock or amaze
anybody okay
it should shock it amaze you to
understand that an address is nothing
more than offset into memory if we view
memory is one big array byte 0 byte 1
byte 2 by 3 by 4 by 5 by 6 by 7 when you
have a pointer all you have is an
integer that contains the offset from
the beginning of memory 473 bytes in
8192 bytes in right you'll send em to
you the phrase word size right when you
actually go to build a processor right
you have to design a data path that can
accommodate data up to a certain size so
you could move it between memory in the
processor easily okay you need to define
a sort of a hardware variable called a
register and it needs to have a certain
basic size and in general you want your
data path to be able to accommodate a
full register worth of data ok that
defines the word size of the system how
big are the registers and how big is the
data path so generally speaking your
registers your pointers and your data
for the rest of your data path are all
the same size and that's called the word
size ok now sometimes you have data
types that are larger than that and they
just require more than one path you know
in some way shape or form through the
data bus in order to deal with that ok
but the systems are designed to handle
data up to a certain size a 32-bit
system the registers the data path 32
bits if you need to deal with more than
that you need to deal with some how do
your math in a more complicated way
using 32-bit registers ok give it up
64-bit numbers we have to deal with
those 32-bit registers ok a 64-bit
system the registers and data path and
whatnot 64 bits wide ok this slide is
really confusing the only thing you
should get from this slide is that
memory is byte oriented not word
oriented so even if I'm dealing with an
integer that's four bytes large ok
even if I'm dealing with a 32-bit system
or a 64-bit system my addresses are
still byte addresses it doesn't matter
that my system uses a four byte data
type my addresses are still measured in
single bytes a pointer still measures
the total number of bytes from 0 so this
is not the right way to think of memory
this is it is in fact true that if you
present some weird address you may be
somewhere in the middle of a data type
you may be in the middle of an integer
right but you can still present that bad
pointer
and then the system will still choke on
it right because you presented a bad
pointer but the addresses are going to
name an offset from zero in memory not
some multiple of a datatype and this is
critically important because even though
my system may be able to accommodate a
64-bit integer a char is still one byte
eight bits right you have to be able to
get to the small things you know if
we're talking about C C's define several
types in several datatypes charge sorts
ends Long's Long's long Sloat's doubles
long doubles and pointers and our
typical 32-bit system we see the chars
are one byte shorts or 2 bytes insert 4
bytes
since it's a 32-bit system Long's are
still 4 bytes long Long's are now 8
bytes floats or 4 bytes doubles are
gonna be double the float or a fights
long double still eight bytes pointers
four bytes okay on a 32-bit system your
pointer size gonna be the same as your
data path size all right you know the
Intel 30 the Intel system it's basically
mirrors that right except for the fact
we see funding and funding this on a so
called long double and we'll talk about
that but that's because there's night
ripoli standard that applies to
floating-point numbers and the Intel
system is able to accommodate that okay
and then if we look at the 64-bit system
we see that in general the data types
are the same size they were on the
32-bit system right one two four eight
but now we see that the long actually is
eight now it's actually able to be
double the size of the end a long long
is still eight floats or doubles or
eight long doubles are now able to
accommodate that you know the same 10
bit standard now an additional 16 bit
standard and we'll talk about that we
talk about floating floating point
numbers pointers are now eight bits
instead of instead of four because we
now have we now the ability to have
64-bit addresses because we have a
64-bit data path byte ordering
so if you think about it and you think
about a binary number the least
significant bits are on the right
correct and the most significant bits
are on the left the same is true for
decimal numbers right my ones place is
here tens hundreds thousands small was
on the right big is on the left if
however I would ask you to label things
you would label the first the second the
third the fourth the fifth you would
count from the left to the right
everybody agree so there are two
different ways we can number bytes if I
say integer has four bytes it's logical
that I number them zero one two three
because that's how we normally number
things or it's logical I number them
zero one two three because that's how we
count bits and digits in a number so we
have two different numbering systems we
use big-endian and little-endian
depending on which way we do this okay
big endian you see right if we take
something that's that's that's you know
zero one two three four five six seven
you see with big endian zero one two
three four five six seven the bytes go
from the left to the right that is to
say the big is at the end little endian
flips the bytes but not the bits each
individual byte 8-bit grouping stays the
same but the ordering of those bytes is
now flipped zero one two three four five
six seven
okay
Intel machines for example use one
ordering Sun machines use another
ordering if you send the value over the
network from one machine to another this
becomes important if you write a value
to a file and read it on another system
it becomes important if you're in a
debugger it becomes important okay
otherwise we don't have to care because
the value is the value if I if I get
them if the value is 19 the value is 19
this system interprets the bits
correctly okay so you can see that
systems that use different byte
orderings the bytes get flipped but the
individual bits do not okay and so we
could write a quick little program and
see that just walks through and shows us
this okay we can see this in a debugger
okay it's important when you're doing
things like the like you're doing the
view you do the bomb lab next right
where you'll actually be able to edit
the build debugger looking at it and it
actually gets really confusing because
as it turns out gdb keeps the same byte
ordering regardless of what type of
system it's being used on because it's a
portable debugger and so it will reverse
the bytes for you so depending upon how
you look at it it will either be native
in which case it'll be big ending in a
little endian or the way gdb renders it
and so you've got to be really careful
to make sure you know what is the system
doing what are my tools doing and that
will help you find values in the in you
know when you're doing things like
debugging assembly pointers well 32-bit
pointers in 32-bit 64-bit pointers or 64
bits
they're basically integers with an
offset from zero and so the Indian rules
apply there to strings the thing to know
about strings is that strings in C are
arrays of characters the idea of a
string is mostly created by C's
libraries okay it 98% does not exist in
the C language proper the only way it
exists in the C language proper
is that a string literal exists you
could say quote ABCD quote and with that
represent is a character array
containing a b c d and null the bit
pattern 0 okay
strings in c are null terminated so if
you if you of the string ABCD ABCD that
is 5 bytes large for for the ABCD and a
fifth one for the null termination
that's how when you pass it into a
library it knows for example in printf
how many to print a b c d no stop ok
there's no byte ordering issue and it's
in with strings because strings are one
byte flip that byte however you want
it's still the same byte okay
so code security example when you're
passing things into functions data types
matter because if somebody passes in a
big type a big value into a function
that has an unsigned type or something
that big value can now look really
negative if you're expecting up to a 5
byte string and someone passes in a ten
Duyck string as will learn come buff lab
it can overwrite extra bytes in memory
generating a security concern so at the
low level these things actually matter
ok bonus extras are slides that we don't
actually use what we leave in the deck
so do you guys have any questions all
right have a great day everybody
take good care
Subtitles End: mo.dbxdb.com