Youtube subtitles download by mo.dbxdb.com
all right so Greene's welcome to the
second exciting addition to fifteen
eighteen to thirteen and fifteen five
thirteen today we get to talk about bits
bytes and integers all right I know this
is gonna shock and amaze everyone in the
class you probably never ever heard this
before okay
computers work in binary look I can
pissed that past things I'm very good at
this this is actually a little trickier
because there's no table here but I can
even do that one it's going to amaze
everybody okay computers work in binary
they don't actually use decimal right
you've all seen the t-shirts right then
you know one zero the number two right
there are one zero types of people those
who understand binary those who don't so
here's my question for you right why do
computers work in binary what's that
transistors only have two states is that
true has an amplifier work push-pull
amplifier you do digital logic indeed so
you do digital logic transistors just
switch okay hypothesizing the
transistors actually can be used for
analog applications also which I think
would be a verifiable hypothesis what's
that so so I mean admittedly there's a
gate current that controls whether it's
on or off if there's an amplification or
a game that's associated with that it's
variable so any rate why why is it
I mean well before they were digital
computers there were analog computers
yes yeah it's easier to distinguish
between on and off then on 1/3 2/3 3/4
7/8 whatever and off right I mean here's
the example I like to use it was much
easier when we had normal light switches
in the room but you know details details
right right now are the lights on or off
the lights on yes and now off ok so if
we call this zero and this one come on
what is that is that 10% or 20% or 30%
or 40% 50% what do you think no I mean
is I mean really how like what
percentage brightness is it you think
maybe 75% what do you think 40 80 help
me out 60 ma'am 70 right
we can't tell forty sixty eighty twenty
seventy you know it's harder right it's
much easier to distinguish between on
and off and that's why we have digital
logic if I have some signal right it's
much easier to tell on from off than it
is somewhere in between now add to that
the fact that we never have pure signals
we have signal and noise right and so I
might take a signal that's exactly 5
volts really it's exactly 5 volts plus
or minus some tolerance right and now if
I go to transfer that signal some of the
leaves
right we lose some and the wire acts as
an antenna and we gain some so our noise
signal is whatever we gain and whatever
we lose right
so it's really hard to have anything
exact when you have things that are
analog you can't copy things right back
in the day right the music was stored on
tape right and you would copy things it
was like a photocopier every copy got a
little worse because you introduced more
noise and lost more signal there was no
way to get it back okay
the good thing about about a digital
signal is that if we say look this is on
this is off we tolerate that in terms of
new ways we tolerate that in terms of
noise if we're anywhere here we can
always reset it to fully on what's
really off if we're anywhere here we can
always reset it to fully on and if we
ever land in this space that's the error
state we've lost too much to no prisoner
okay so with digital signals we can
easily sample to tell what we have a 1
or a 0 and we can keep that going
forever not like analog where it's very
hard to tell exactly what we have and
where it only degenerates it's
unsurprising and amazing to most of you
that binary as you guys seem to get
right has two states on/off and then our
numbering system is based upon that so
we have two digits your own one so we
have the two the zeros place that's the
ones place the two to the ones place
that's the twos place the two squared
place that's the fours place two cubes
place that's the eights place
16s plays thirty twos plays 64 plays 128
plays 2d six plays 512 plays and so on
right it works just like math did in
kindergarten right we knew the ones
place the tens place the hundreds plays
the thousands place right used to
rearrange you these little things the
unit that was a little square right the
line that was ten right the tens block
that was ten tens into a big square
the cube right there was 10 of those
things stacked on top of each other for
a thousand or a hundred no there's 10
pens thousand yes sorry the ones tens
hundreds thousand you get past that was
in kindergarten and so it's the same way
right we have the ones place the twos
place the fours place the eights place
that is to say to the zero to the 1 2
squared to the 3rd just like 10 to the 0
10 to the 1st 10 to the 2nd 10 to the
3rd 10 to the 4th and so on and that's
that binary is really tough for people
to deal with because it takes so many
digits to represent something right it's
just a pain if you've got to deal with
it so when programmers are dealing with
binary but want a more compressed
representation we often times turn to
hexadecimal hexadecimals base 16
numbering system 1 16 256 and so on
right 16 to the 0 16 to the one 16 to
the two 16 to the 3 16 to the 4 16 to
the 5 16 to the six right blah blah blah
blah blah the good thing about it is
it's a power of 2 system so every 4
binary digits can be represented as a
single hex digit that's really nice
because I have these groupings of 4 okay
and if I want to know what bits you know
you know what bit 10 is I only have to
you know to decode one of those
groupings right it's very easy decimal
is much harder right these decimals not
a power of two okay so you can't tightly
group the bits okay there's no way of
just taking a group of powers of two and
having it you know densely represent a
power of 10 right if I take these two
bits
I have zero right through three if I
take these three bits I have zero
through seven right seven you know seven
is less than 10
if I take these four bits I have 0
through 15 15 is more than 10 I don't
have exactly 10 right whereas if I take
a group of 4 bits I have 0 through 15
that's exactly 16 digits so people you
know use commonly the decimal numbering
systems because it's convenient for us
it's not just because we have 10 fingers
and 10 toes and whatnot right although
we like to say that it's because it's
for common purposes and easy for us to
wrap our brains around having 10 digits
we don't need a big lookup table to see
what some digit means okay so the
logical things for us to use our power
of 8 octal or power of 16 hexadecimal to
represent binary they're very close to
what we commonly use as a power of 10
but their powers of 2 so it breaks up
nicely
sometimes programmers do use octal but
as it turns out our brains don't stay
exploded 16 16 is still very comfortable
for us and so most of the time
programmers will use hexadecimal you
could imagine a numbering system that
had 32 characters okay most of the
alphabet plus 0 through 9 okay but at a
certain point we get really hard to
remember like what exactly is Jake just
more state than we're used to dealing
with data representations when we deal
with programs when we deal with data
types the data types are ultimately
represented in binary okay a character
tends to be one byte eight bits a short
tends to be two bytes 16 bits int 4
bytes sorry it's 4 byte 16 bits short 2
bytes 8 bits long
right on most systems it's still 4 bits
except on 64-bit systems right the
current generation and I'm having
trouble with math today on most systems
along is still 4 bits ok 4 bytes
32 bits on the 64 bit systems it
actually is now larger it is 64 bits
okay long Long's 64-bits across all
systems floats four bits across all
systems doubles 8 bits across all
systems along double its eight bits on
most older architecture 32-bit machines
on Intel it's a weird 10 or 12 bits and
we'll talk about why on 32-bit systems
and 10 or 16 bits on 64-bit systems why
10 you know 10 or 12 or 10 or 16 it has
to do with the native format on the
Intel processor or using the standard I
Triple E format that the processor also
supports pointers okay memory is
addressed right basically with index
into it bytes 0 byte 1 by 2 by 3 by 4 so
memory is address with an integer
basically okay so pointers are gonna be
you know 4 bytes
okay 32 bits on 32-bit systems or 8
bytes 64 bits on 64-bit systems what
does it mean we say we have a 64-bit
system that means the register size is
64 bits besides the data path is 64 bits
the basic size of data that the system
deals with easily is 64 bits what
happens if it has small smaller data
that's okay it just doesn't use all
those bits what happens if it has larger
data well that's okay but it might take
two paths two trips through the thing or
in the case of floating-point numbers
that's using sort of a separate separate
part of the processor um so what to say
we've all heard about boolean logic
logic involving true and false right you
probably took some logic class over in
philosophy that dealt with this or play
with a little bit in high school but the
basic idea is that we deal with ORS and
Anne's and exclusive ORS and things like
that an end condition is only true if
both of the constituent states are true
you can eat dinner if you have a fork
and a knife okay you
can't cut your food with one of the
other okay and that's a logic land and
so it's only true if both conditions are
true otherwise it's false you can leave
the class when the class is over or the
fire alarm rings so you leave if class
ends or the fire alarm rings or fire
alarm rings one class ends the not
operation is oppositeday you played this
game as a kid everything that's true is
false everything that's false is true so
if I negate something I take it from his
from false to a true or true to false
from 0 or 1 or 1 to 0 I'm an exclusive
or is like an or condition except for
this state here when they're both true
it's actually false okay so this is like
we do were a little kid and you know
your your your father said well you can
have an ice-cream sandwich or a cookie
what your father meant is you can have
one or the other but not both if you
follow as a computer scientist your
father might have said you can
exclusive-or right there put that cell
phone away
okay right so exclusive-or is true one
or the other but not both
and so these form the basis for these
logical operations you know for the
basis for a lot of decision-making and
binary systems and here you can see
we're applying the bitwise operators and
or exclusive or and not to two inputs
and binary and the operator is applied
to corresponding bits in both of the
operands 1 & 1 is 1 0 & 0 is 0 ok and so
we see we only have a 1 when both
columns are 1 it's the end operator here
you can see we have it we're going to
have a 1 anytime we have a 1 in any
columns and either column the only time
it's 0 is when both columns are 0 that's
the or operator the exclusive or
operator is going to be true
only when there's a 1 in exactly one of
the two plate corresponding places not
if they're both 0 not if they're both 1
1 0 0 1 okay boom func 1 0 0 1 0 there 0
there ok and not the gate just opposite
day okay we refer to the width of a
number it's how many digits there are so
if we say the you know the width of an
integer in this particular system is 16
bits we mean there are 16 binary digits
now sometimes we use integers not really
to perform not really to count things
okay but just as bit sets where each bit
represents something different like
let's say I wanted to take attendance I
could say you're gonna be represented by
bit zero and you're gonna be represented
by bit one and you're gonna be
represented by bit too and you're gonna
be represented by bit three and your bid
is four and your bid is five and your
bit of six and you're a bit of seven and
your bid is eight and your bid is nine
your bid is ten and so on and if you
show up to class we flip you're a bit on
if you don't we flip your bit off now I
have an integer acting as a bit set and
to say it's acting as a set it tests
membership in the set or not in the set
if the bid is on you're in the set if
your bid is off you're not in the set
you weren't there okay so now what well
now I can pound to find a particular
position to be yours so let's say your
bit three I'll have some pound define
which name Josh that'll say pound to
find Josh to be one left shifted by
three now that's your bit and now I can
do and or to set your bit attendance
Eagles attendance or Josh bitwise or and
that flips are a bit on keeping all the
bits the same I can ask if you were
there right how would I find out if you
were there take the end josh present
equals attendance and josh because all
the rest of the bits of josh is zero
except for the one bit that represents
you and if that's also true in the
attendance set then the result will be
non zero or true we agree so that's what
this sly is talking about okay now what
okay a little more story that bitwise
operations and you can walk those bite
through those by hand if you like um
keep in mind the distinction between
bitwise operations okay and the logical
operations right notice to ampersand
signs versus one notice two pipes versus
one that's a key difference okay
because these are the logical operations
these don't look at the individual bits
these look at the integer as a whole and
ask the question is it zero or not if
it's zero it's false if it's not as a
whole it's true okay and so now what we
do is with your formal logical
operations but on the whole thing we
take the whole integer and view it as
true or false if all the bits are zero
its false if any bit is one it's true
and now we perform the operation that's
the difference between the two
ampersands and two pipes and you know
and the bang two ampersands is the
logical dealing with the whole thing is
one two pipes the bank versus the tilt
ok this takes the whole thing as opposed
to a single ampersand a single pipe or a
single bang which does the bitwise
operations okay so you can go ahead and
close your laptop excellent thank you
these very suspicious when you quit
taking notes of the instructor walks by
might leave the instructor to believe in
laptops being used for social media okay
I'll be have some more examples and you
guys can walk through in your own time
there um this is sort of an interesting
one that I do want to pause and talk
about that P and star P that's a very
very common construct for pointers
because referencing and no pointer is
bad right if you reference the null
point or what happens same falls
right the point Durer's value is 0 it's
a null pointer it's not a valid address
you dereference that and you get a seg
fault
okay so if we look at this P when an
operand to an ampersand ampersand
operation is going to be evaluated as
true or false if it's a null pointer its
false if it's not it's true C uses
what's called short-circuit evaluation
meaning it doesn't evaluate any more of
a logical expression than it needs to to
know the result if P is false
is there any way this expression can be
true no because false and anything is
false right so C stops there never
looking to see what star P is since it
never dereferences star P you never get
the seg fault does that make sense so
this value is going to be 0 or false if
P is null otherwise it's going to be we
repeat the value of whatever P points to
yes so
right so this is checking to see if P is
false or if the value is zero right as
opposed to if I would do just this if
star P okay then it would blow up with P
was null so if I want to take something
if I want to if I want to you know
borrow a car there's a problem with my
car count to zero you can do it P 10
star P that's that is perfectly valid
see most people would prefer this
construct because it's shorter but it's
you know you can do it with a you can do
it with an if statement just the same
yes well so what I mean look at this
expression this expression is going to
be a true or false expression because
that's the result of an ampersand amber
and percent operator so basically it's
like looking at star P as a true or
false value okay but we're checking to
make sure that it's valid before we do
does that make sense so it forces it to
false in the case we would otherwise be
invalid okay left shift and right shift
left arrow three that says take whatever
bits pattern we have and shoves three
zeros to the right of it in effect
pushing it to the left okay given that
all data types we saw have a fixed width
if I ship things inside to the laughter
okay this stuff on the left is just
going to disappear it's gonna fall off
the other side it's called the left
shift okay when it comes to a right
shift we're gonna have two different
types of right shift a logical right
shift is it is exactly the same we shove
some bits on the right on the we shove
some bits on the left pushing everything
to the right if I shove in one bit on
the left 1 bits gonna fall off the right
side okay
so in the common case a left shift has
the effect of multiplying by a power of
two if I left shift by one the thing in
the one position becomes a to the thing
in the 2 position becomes a for the
thing in the four position becomes an 8
so it has the effect of left shifting of
multiplying by 2 right for every time I
left shift until a point where I start
losing precision at the at the left hand
side a right shift therefore has the
effect of dividing by 2 okay obviously
truncating as things only fall off it
doesn't round up but as will learn about
shortly there's another number
representation okay called two's
complement and with two's complement
when we talk about it you'll learn that
it's really important to preserve the
left side bit if the left side bit is a
1 it's really important to keep it a 1
and if the left side the leftmost bit
starts out as a 0 it's really important
to keep it a 0 and we'll talk about why
soon ok meaning today and a rhythmic
right shift respects that so if the high
bit is a 1 it inserts once if the high
bits is a zero inserts zeros okay a
logical right shift doesn't it always
insert zeros and again when we talk
about two's complement in just a few
minutes we'll talk about why that is
ok if you shift by more or less than the
words by less than zero right that's
undefined in other words the C standard
says that if you try to shift by a
negative number there's no guarantee
that's equivalent to a right shift right
right left shift by negative 5 that's
not necessarily the same as right
shifting by 5 the result is undefined
similarly if I have a 32-bit type and
shift all my bits out there's no
guarantee that I'm left with zeros ok
the result of that is undefined
the reason for this is that part of the
philosophy of C was that the operations
the basic operations in C should be the
same as whatever the basic operations
are in the actual hardware they didn't
want to impose new requirements because
a new requirement could mean that one
operation and C like this would require
multiple operations on the processor and
they wanted to minimize that the the
situations where that was the case to
make these operators really align with
the processor operators and since
processors don't necessarily do these
things they didn't make them
requirements of the language that's they
didn't hide that complexity
okay so we see with with an original
argument of 0 1 1 0 0 0 1 0 if I left
shift by 3 this one is moving over 1 2 3
positions okay so these three positions
fall off the edge these 3 bits come over
here my new 3 bits are over here if I
right shift logical bike by 2 these two
positions are gonna fall off that 1 0
goes away everything else shifts to the
right and two zeros get put in here a
logical right shift is gonna do the same
thing in this case because rhythmatic
right --chips gonna do the same thing in
this case because my high order bit is
over 0 but if I come down here where my
high order bit is a 1 here I'm shifting
ones in instead of zeros and a rhythmic
shift when you do a right shift she adds
in whatever that bit already is okay
there is no such thing as an arithmetic
left shift you always put zeros in on a
left shift the lodger the owner of
thematic turn out to be the same we'll
talk about why shortly you have a
question of destruction okay okay
I knew I should have looked at these
slides before class they put math on my
slides and that's putting ethan yes well
if you shift by the word size the
expected behavior most humans would have
would be that'll be all zeroes but at
the point in time where they were
drafting the C standard there was some
processors that didn't do that but if
you tried to shift by more than the word
size it went do you guys get that on
tape you sure they got it okay okay and
so they didn't make it a requirement
because they didn't want a situation
where the processor had a shift
operation yet the C operation that the
correspondent to that had to do a shift
and then an assignment whose question
was that does that answer your question
okay and then once they did that they
wanted to carry that behavior forward
because they wanted the old they wanted
the new compilers to be backward
compatible compatible with the old
source and so that's where we are okay
this is terrible I've got the funny e
Riemann's something and subscripts and
superscripts man exponents
I think we've learned in third grade
that they use a dot instead of an X from
math for multiplication sometimes okay
this is designed to look academic and
complex it really is very easy okay if
you think about a binary number each
digit and a binary number represents a
power of two two to the zero to the 1/2
squared to the third to the fourth two
to the eighth and so on 1 2 4 8 16 32 64
128 blah blah blah that is the value
associated with the corresponding bit
position right bit position zero has a
value of two to the zero bit position
one has a value of 2 to the 1/5 position
2 2 2 2 2 squared bit position 3 to the
3rd or 8 and so on so if I want to know
the value of a binary number all I do is
I look at it bit after bit after bit and
I ask does you know is bit 0 1 is to say
is 2 to the 0 present if it is I add it
to my to my you to my value I then move
on to bit 1 is 2 to the 1 present is
that bit of 1 if so I add it to my
running sum is bit you know to present
if so add 4 to my running sum is bit 3
present if it's 1 I add 8 to my son if
it's 0 I don't and that's how I find the
value of a binary number just like
that's how I find the value of a decimal
number just like in kindergarten when
you took the number of you know the
number of single squares and added it to
the number of rows and added it to the
number of you know a bit of big squares
one unit plus 3 tens plus 4 hundreds
plus 3 thousands right that's all this
says start at bit 0 working your way to
the highest bit the width minus 1 why
the width minus 1 if I have 16 bits its
0 through 15 rather than 1 through 16
- to the zero that way we get the one
and so this basically says we're bid
zero through through bit 31 if we're
dealing with a 32-bit number right take
whether or not that bit is present
whether or not that bit is a 0 or a 1
and multiply it by the value of the bit
- 2 0 1 - 1 - 2 squared 4 - 2 third
eight and this is the 1 or 0 that's in
that bit position and that's all it says
find the value of a binary number by
walking from bit 0 through the last bit
adding the value of that position if and
only if the corresponding bid is 1
otherwise add 0 does that overly
complicated math make sense to everybody
okay now this is two's complement this
is the way we represent negative numbers
I'm going to switch over to the
chalkboard for a minute here
[Music]
let's start counting in binary 0 1 1 0 1
1 1 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 0 1 1 1
every agree ok and this is sort of like
if I were counting in you know in
decimal 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 and then I
carry 1 0 the difference is I end up
carrying much sooner here 0 1 carry 1
plus 1 is 0 carry the 1 1 and 0 is 1 1 1
plus 1 is 0 carry the 1 1 + 1 is 0 carry
the 1 1 0 0 make sense 1 0 0 + 1 is 1 0
1 1 0 1 + 1 is 1 and 1 is 0 carry the 1
1 + 0 is 1 1 1 1 0 + 1 is 1 1 1 1 1 1 +
1 is 1 + 1 is 0 carry the 1 1 M 1 is 0
carry the 1 1 M 1 is 0 carry the 1 we
agree in this example I'm generating new
bits as I need them but in a process or
I have a certain width 16 bits 32 bits
64 bits so let's say that I have a 3 bit
processor here
I actually had a memory 0 0 0 then 0 0 1
then 0 1 0 then 0 1 1 then 1 0 0 then 1
0 1 then 1 1 0 then 1 1 1 but when I do
this carry I have a problem I only have
3 bits I'm back to 0
do you see that I've started over and
now if I add 1 I'm back here right ok so
let me ask you something
if I have X plus y equals 0 what is y
everybody you breathe
I have 1 1 1 plus y equals 0 what is y
equal what's the obvious simple answer
I'm looking for
what did I do over here y equals
negative x right what am I looking for
here y equals negative 1 1 1 right
anybody disagree we all happy so what
did I add to 1 1 1 to make it 0 1
something's wrong
I just found that one equals negative
seven how did you guys know math class
Mike Bell thank you how many people in a
math class they should you like the
point nine bar equals equals equals one
guys remember that how do you how do you
believe them I still don't believe them
I did that prove a thousand times
okay this looks a little weird doesn't
it according to this one one one equals
negative one do you agree
okay let's go with that for a minute
let's assume that 1 1 1 is equal to
negative 1
ha
okay what's a negative one plus one okay
let's add one just for symmetry is this
working out do you guys agree this is
working okay okay so hypothetically
speaking if one one one is a negative
one
this sort of works right let's play
around some more
let's suggest that I take a number any
number and I complement it we agree that
those are complements and I add them
together what do I always get what's
that all one's right negative one we
agree so this would suggest that if I
take these two things and add them
together I get negative 1 what happens
if I take these things and I add and I
add them together and I add 1 what am I
gonna get every time do you agree if I
take a number and compliment it add the
two numbers together and add 1 I get all
zeros right
so X plus the complement of X plus one
is equal to zero
do we all agree therefore x equals
negative the complement of X plus one do
we agree so the complement of X plus one
equals negative X do we agree so now
let's say we Bates the system of math
based upon this where positive numbers
non-negative numbers or whatever they
are negative numbers are their
complement plus one well in theory if I
add 1 to the complement of a number plus
1 its negative value if I add 1 to
negative 5
should I get closer to or farther than
or farther away from 0 closer to right
if you add a positive number to a
negative number and you get closer to 0
these until you cross 0 okay and how
much closer should I get if I add 1
did you believe one okay so if this is X
and we know this is negative x we all
agree I'm sorry where's my negative x my
negative x is the complement of this
plus one right okay so my negative x is
going to be the complement of this 0 1 0
0 1 plus 1 1 and 1 is 0 carry a 1 do we
agree and we just showed that if we add
these together what do we get 0 0 carry
a 1 0 carry a 1 0 carry a 1 0 that one
drops off the other end okay all zeros
so now if I add 1 to this ok 0 1 0 1 1
and I add X to negative x plus 1 that's
basically what I did right what should I
get I should get 1 okay so what do I get
if I add X to negative X plus 1
zero and one is a 1 right everything
else is the same I get my 1 you see that
so this is what we call complement
arithmetic in complement arithmetic we
represent non-negative numbers as we
always did before we represent negative
numbers by complementing an adding 1 why
that makes them the additive inverse
does that make sense the only problem we
have with this is distinguishing what is
in two's complement representation and
what is in normal representation because
if I give you a number like 1 0 1 1 0
you don't know if that's a positive
number or a negative number you don't
know if you should to complim you know
subtract 1 and complement it to find its
real value or if you should take it at
face value so here's what we do we use
the highest bit as assignment if the
highest bit is a 1 we interpret it as
two's complement that is to say if we
want to know its value we subtract 1
negate it and then make it to negative
of the resulting value if the leading
bit is a 0 we leave it alone this says
that we have
negative numbers ranging from 1 0-0 0 or
whatever right 2 1 1 1 1 we have
non-negative numbers ranging from 0 0 0
0 to 0 1 1 1
do you agree if you add 1 to this
positive number the largest positive
number you get 1 0 0 0 which brings you
here that would be the most negative
number because remember how this works
this is the most negative number and as
we add things to it we bring it closer
to 0 does that make sense so in two's
complement arithmetic the bit pattern 1
followed by all zeros is always the most
negative number the bit pattern 0
followed by all ones is always the most
positive number does that make sense the
bit pattern 0 is 0 do you see why that
is the way it is a lot of people
memorize this stuff ok and they spend
their lifetime trying to memorize this
there's no reason to memorize it if you
think about it it makes sense if I know
that I'm using this as the sign bit
everything else follows from there I
know this is the most negative number
because anything I add to a negative
number brings it closer to 0 ok I know
this is the most positive number because
if I add want to be cut wraps around 2
negative does that make sense
on the non-negative side of the number
line we're adding to zero as we take all
zeros and start to add to it mink on the
negative side of the number line we're
starting with the most negative number
one zero zero zero and adding to it to
bring it back to zero where I have 1 1 1
1 plus 1 is 0 1 1 1 1 we already said
always represents what pattern what's
that
negative 1 right 1 1 1 1 right subtract
1 1 1 1 0 complement 0 0 0 1
so you can memorize this make your brain
full or you can realize why it all works
1 1 1 1 plus 1 is 0
anything plus 1 that 0 is equal to
negative 1 ok and we go from there
alright so that's gonna be our most
negative number all the way over
starting with that adding this back to
bring us closer to 0 ok all right
switching back over to slides
so as we look over on the right side of
this and we see another scary fraction
and a fraction equation what are we
looking at well there's nothing to be
scared of here this looks a lot like
this side right here we sum from 0 to
with minus 1 here we sum from 0 to with
minus 2 y with minus 2 that leftmost bit
is the sign bit whether the number is
negative or positive we're going to be
adding the things that aren't the sign
bit either adding them to 0 or adding
them to the most negative number so we
sum up those things does that make sense
in the event of a positive non-negative
number its 0 plus that sum in the event
of a negative number it's the most
negative number plus that sum now we
look at that sign bit the X to the X sub
W minus 1 bit the leftmost bit if it is
a 0 we start but with 0 and we add
everything from there so this term is
going to be a 0 and we add that so if
this bit is 0 its negative 0 which is 0
times something which is still 0 its 0
plus everything else
if however that leftmost bit is 1 it's
the most negative number right and so
we're gonna start there and add our way
back so this is gonna be 1 times 2 to
the W minus 1 times the bit position of
that leftmost bit that's going to give
us the most negative number right we
said the bit pattern 1 and all zeros is
always the most negative number so now
it's the most negative number plus all
of this which brings us closer to 0 does
that make sense we can't quite get to 0
because 0 is going to be the bit
patterns all 0 0 in the high-order bit
and 0 in all the low-order bits 0 plus 0
you see that what's the value of the
moat of the most negative number the
sign bits on this is all off what's the
value of negative one the sign bits on
and everything else is on these the most
negative number plus everything else
which leaves us one short of a zero make
sense okay now is zero negative or
positive so some mathematicians in the
class are trying to answer that question
legitimately with respect to our number
line zero comes out of the same side of
the number line as positive numbers
because it begins with a zero right it's
direct not two's complement that means
that we can represent a number that's
more our most negative number is more
negative than our most positive number
because our our non negative side of the
number range goes from zero to something
our negative side of the number range
goes from negative one to something
they're the same number of bits so the
zero comes out of the positive side of
the number line does that make sense
it's the non negative side of the number
line so my most my largest greatest you
know non negative number is going to be
one smaller and it's absolute value than
my greatest negative number because the
zero is coming out of that side of the
number line okay
that's why my most negative number is
one greater than my most positive number
do you see that don't memorize it
there's tons of this stuff that you can
mindlessly memorize but you don't need
to you just need to keep in mind that it
is what it is for a reason zero comes
out of this side of the number line it's
zero through something not 1 through
something right this is negative 1
through negative 2 to the W minus 1 this
is zero through to the W minus 1 minus 1
why I'm starting at 0 so I get 1 I get I
don't get quite as far okay
we talked about the fact that 0 is
always 0 we talked about the fact with
unsigned numbers all ones is migrators
bit pattern we talked about the other
bit patterns that are common right all
ones is going to be a negative 1 a 1 in
all zeros is going to be the most
negative number okay we talked about why
it's the most negative number plus all
the ones that brings us to a negative 1
plus 1 add 1 to a negative 1 and you see
all ones plus 1 is going to be 0 1 plus
1 is 0 carry the 1 1 + 1 0 carry the 1 1
0 carry the 1 1 plus 1 is 0 carry 1 1
plus 1 is 0 there's nowhere to carry the
1 we throw it away we're all zeros so it
all works out you guys see that ok
and so given a particular number of bits
you can figure out what the maximum
sizes are if you do this math you must
be drunk and smart you get it right must
be drunk smart and careful even while
drunk
um don't do that ok use the pound of
fives all right if you want to know the
maximum size of n sidelong your system
use you long max right that way when you
compile it on the next generation 128
bit processors 10 years from now right
it still works
so okay we talked about these conversion
things these are the functions we looked
at before here's what's worth seen if I
take my sign number and I take my
unsigned number and I take the bit
pattern here I have the bit patterns
ranging from zero to all ones for a
while it doesn't matter whether I'm
dealing with a sign type or unsigned
type it's exactly the same however once
I add one to this and I get one zero
zero in the case of an unsigned number I
keep growing 7 plus 1 is 8 plus 1 is 9
plus 1 is 2 n in heat in this case it
suddenly becomes the most negative
number why look at my bit pattern the
most negative number plus nothing you
guys see that okay and then from there
we continue monotonically increasing why
we're adding one eventually here we get
to the bit pattern 1 1 0 we add 1 it
becomes 0 here we get to negative 1 and
we add 0 in either case that makes sense
ok so if we look at two's complements
number line and the unsigned number line
okay we see that they overlap in a
particular range and then there's this
crossover that happens in the higher
part of that range we're the most
negative number if you look at it as an
unsigned number is a isn't is you know a
big unsigned number right so if I take a
look at my mug at my uh my my biggest on
my most negative number that's a 1 with
all zeros
okay that's gonna be immediately above
my two's-complement maximum why my
two's-complement maximum is 1 1 1 1 past
that is 1 0 0 0 ok so if I look at that
here I become negative 1 1 1 becomes 1 0
0 here I'm just adding a 1 1 1 1 becomes
1 0 0 0 great I'm not doing anything
different with that leading one here I
grow monotonically from there right here
okay what am i doing I'm adding back and
growing this way and see if you write a
number 2 3 4 5 that number by default is
signed constants by default are signed
and see if you want them to be unsigned
append a you after them okay having said
that my default types like int and long
and float are all signed if you want
them to be unsigned add the unsigned
qualifier if there's a mix of signed and
unsigned values in the same expression 1
variables assigned type and other
variables unsigned type the sign values
are cast to an unsigned so if you have
signed plus and unsigned it
automatically takes the sign value cast
it to an unsigned and then your math
proceeds as unsigned arithmetic
so zero versus zero unsigned negative
one okay a constant so these are a set
of puzzles and the question is what's
the relationship between these two
numbers zero sign and zero unsigned well
their answer is they're both equal
what's the do of the relationship
between negative 1 and zero well
negative 1 is less than zero okay and
that's evaluated as signed right because
this is signed and this is signed
negative 1 and 0 unsigned well now I
have an unsigned type so my negative 1
is cast to it unsigned if I take a
negative 1 bit pattern and I interpret
it as unsigned it's a big number right
it's bigger than 0 okay and you can walk
through these the rest of these as an
exercise to the reader if you have any
questions email the list ask them to
recitation on sp1 a presentation of
Monday email the list to drop by for
office hours but these are all just
puzzles that came up the idea that the
first thing you do is if you have mixed
mode is convert side values to unsigned
values and then you do the
interpretation the bit pattern is
maintained but it's reinterpreted it can
have the effect of adding or subtracting
2 to the width right in other words if I
take a signed number and interpret it as
an unsigned number the higher values are
gonna become negative values in the
event that I've an expression containing
assigned an unsigned integer the int is
cast unsigned first then the arithmetic
proceeds is unsigned but it um I forgot
to ask how far they got in the other
section is there's actually two days of
notes we'll go for another five notes
we may not all line with them exactly
that's okay this time normally we will
all right so sign extension if I have a
32-bit number okay a four byte type a
four byte int and I cast it to a long
long somehow there are more bits what do
I put into those extra high order bits
well if it's an unsigned number I put in
zeros because I want to add nothing to
keep the value the same if it's a sign
number I want to do sign extension I
want to take that high order bit and
extend it to fill that space why if it's
an unsigned number I'm sorry if it's a
if it's a non-negative number that high
order bid is going to be zero so by sign
extending I'm adding in zeroes perfect
but if it's a one this is a negative
number represented in two's complement
if I add zeros it will be interpreted as
a not as a non-negative number right
because the high order bits will no
longer be assigned bit so it's clear my
high-water bit needs to stay a one the
good news is remember how this works one
followed by as many zeros as you have is
always what the most negative number so
if I take the most negative number and I
add in and I pad the rest of it with
ones I'm bringing myself back to where I
was before now adding the rest of the
bits does that make sense so in the case
of a negative number I sign extent
because that means all those ones added
together starts out with a much more
negative number but I add a bunch of
stuff to it which gives me exactly what
I had before plus exactly what I had
before
so I've done nothing to the value of
that number did that make sense
if I have a bit pattern all ones for
example does it matter if I have two
ones or three ones or four ones or five
ones or ten ones what's that know what
does that what is that value what's that
- one negative one right
always so if I have the bit pattern all
ones except the last bit of zero what's
that gonna be give it out - - always
does that make sense
it doesn't matter how many ones are
there because I'm adding back to the
most negative number if I have more ones
I'm starting out with a more negative
number but then adding a bunch more to
it and so here we see a sign extension
example okay no magic to this okay I
have 15 to 13 when I sign extend the
zero extends to a zero I have negative
15 to 13 when I sign extend the one
expands to more ones if I convert from a
larger type to a smaller type it's gonna
try the reverse of this and simply whack
off the high-order bits that works as
long as they weren't needed if however
they weren't all ones or aren't weren't
all zeros and I whack off something else
I've changed the value of that number
right okay
so summary if it's an unsigned number we
add zeroes there's no two's complement
there if it's a signed number we do sign
extension that way if it's a high bid to
0 we add zeroes if the hybrids have one
it's a two's complement number we add
once no loss in sign extending yes yes
when you talk about you talk about left
shifting a right trip thing so when I
when I write shift I have to do the sign
extension and you're exactly right this
is why to make sure that if I have a
two's complement number I preserve the
value so if it's so this is interesting
question if I use the right shift
operator is it an arithmetic or a
logical right shift in in C in Java
they're different operators there's two
greater there's two you know greater
than signs versus three in C there's
only one Operator and my memory of the
standard actually is that it doesn't
require it be anything although
generally it's interpreted most modern
languages interpreted as an arithmetic
shift meet and a-rhythm-etic shit even
for unsigned let me not tell any lies
let me tell you to try because the
standard doesn't actually say but there
is a convention of seemingly among
compiler writers to give it a try then
you'll know let is know next class my
belief is that it's going to do sign
extension in all cases but let's
checking on that okay truncating it's
the same thing it's basically a mod
operation if those leading bits are not
all ones or a signed number not all
zeros for an unsigned number and it
actually loses stuff
it keeps the remainder right
and throws away sort of how many times
it spins around it's modular arithmetic
okay you can walk through that example
in your honor that's a long version of
the old same thing we had before we'll
pick up with addition to get
multiplication shifting next class have
a great day everybody
Subtitles End: mo.dbxdb.com