Youtube subtitles download by mo.dbxdb.com
welcome to this exciting fourth edition
15 18 - 13 15 5 13 we're today and only
today we get to talk about
floating-point numbers yeah I'm excited
all right the background okay look
fractions are a pain in the ass you
learned that in like fourth grade right
I mean they are just a pain they're
still a pain they always were a pain at
the end of the day our numbering system
that we like to think of things in is
decimal right and the problem with the
decimal based numbering system is it
can't represent everything perfectly
cleanly right like 1/3 repeating right
what a pain in the ass okay a binary
number system is gonna be the same way
there's some fractions that are just not
perfectly representable in Pounder
powers of two furthermore when we are
imagining the set of real numbers we had
infinite precision right if I give you
any pair of you know of real numbers you
can put a number between them infinite
precision right the numbers go all the
way left they go all the way right and
there's no distance between them but
that doesn't work in a world of finite
memory it's not only do we have this
problem we can't represent things that
aren't powers of two perfectly but we
also can't represent things to some
arbitrary level of precision all right
and so there are two ways we can
basically deal with this one is what is
called fixed point numbers and in others
what are called floating point numbers
okay fixed point numbers are essentially
a different way of thinking about
integers okay I remember I was a little
kid my grandfather ran a business and he
used one of these old-school adding
machines and he would sit there and he
would add up the different stuff he was
selling he sold coins and he would add
up the coins was adding machine right
though the value like this is a $20 coin
there's 25 dollar coins there's a $32
coin this was 18 dollar coin this is a
52 cent coin blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
and just pound it all in on this adding
machine and then he would have the total
on this little ribbon right and when he
was typing in these numbers like twenty
two dollars and thirty five dollars and
forty five dollars and forty five
dollars and twenty seven cents he would
never hit the decimal point it was 4200
3700 sixty-three 27 why is it that he
would never hit the decimal point I mean
it's 63 dollars and 27 cents
63 dollars and 27 you know out of a
hundred cents 63 point two seven why did
he never hit the decimal point ever the
whole time I watched him as a little kid
he never used the decimal point in some
sense he was just valuing everything his
sense right what's another way of
thinking of that it's a fixed point he
knew the right two digits were gonna be
pennies why would he waste his time
hitting the decimal point okay
that's the fixed point system we have
two digits past the you know the decimal
we have that we have though you know we
have the the integer component here and
then we have the next n digits some
fixed number of digits of the fractional
component that's it okay if you're
thinking about numbers in terms of
powers of two you just think of it in
terms of scientific notation okay if I
have a fixed you know point system and I
want three you know three places worth
of decimal right you can imagine that
whatever a number I have is actually
multiplied by 10 to the negative third
right I just don't write the 10 to the
negative third part because I know it
it's fixed point
the problem with fixed point is not very
flexible you fix the point right it
worked great for my grandfather because
he didn't deal with half cents right
nothing he sold was worth you know 63
27 and you know 1/2 cents $63 you know
27 and 1
you know eighth of a cent didn't work
that way right he always had 2 digits
after the decimal but sometimes it's not
the way it works you might work with
some very small values and then some
very large values and since you have a
fixed amount of memory you have a
decision to make how much of that memory
do I want to use to represent the range
the bigness of the value and how much of
that memory do I want to reuse to
represent the precision am I looking
through a telescope or a microscope if
I'm looking for a microscope I don't
want to have a fixed point system with a
lot of digits to the left of the decimal
place there's nothing that big it's all
a fraction if I'm looking through a
telescope at a planet right
I can't measure accurately enough to
care about fractions I need to measure
big things I need all of my decimal
plate of my all by my storage to the
left of that decimal place right and
then for things in between you might
want to move that so that's the freedom
we have with a floating-point system
does that make sense it lets that point
float so we can capture larger numbers
and smaller numbers with more accuracy
but it has some natural challenges right
because I'm doing math and I'm letting
my decimal place or in this case my
binary place you know float around the
problem is that if I have a really big
number it doesn't have the capacity to
have a lot of precision when it comes to
the fractions right and if I have a
fractional number it doesn't have the
capacity to store something big so when
I multiply those two there's a natural
tension right am I going to lose the you
know lose the ability to have the
magnitude you know the integers with
what am I going to lose the ability to
have the precision in the fraction how
how is that point gonna float and so in
a lot of math where we understand what
the range is
and the range is fairly stable we use
fixed point arithmetic okay we don't we
don't use floating point numbers we
simply use integers and as part of our
code we understand where that point
actually is but in a lot of math we
don't either because we haven't done the
analysis so the problem is dynamic we
need that decimal point to float or that
binary point to float and so we use rely
upon floating point numbers so like
integers floating point numbers are
going to be different than real numbers
you know in that they're not boundless
they have a minimum value and they have
a maximum value
unlike integers there's gonna be what we
call rounding right really a type of
approximation okay that's gonna happen
because with numbers closer to zero our
number line is going to be more dense
there's simply more point on our number
line with numbers farther from zero
they're gonna be farther apart to get us
that magnitude okay at the end of the
day we're dealing with binary everything
we're dealing with is coded as zero zero
zero zero zero one zero one one one zero
one one one whatever there are discrete
points on our number line we can't
change that if we have a 16-bit number
we have a certain number of points in
that number line if we have a 32-bit
number we have another number of points
in that number line right we have a
64-bit number right you get a greater
number of points on the number line but
that's it
given some width of number we have a
certain number of points in their number
line we can change the way we label them
we can change how we interpret them but
we can't give ourselves more okay we can
take this bunch closer to you know this
bunch over here and label them in
smaller steps and this bunch over here
and label them in bigger steps but we
can't change the total number of points
okay so the I Triple E is an engineering
organization right how many you how many
you know computer electrical engineers
we have any raise your hands all right
so you guys know this organization right
what is it
yo it out what what is i triple e stand
for
oh come on don't look it up who's it
who's double who's a couple in here
you've heard of this the yeah forget the
prepositions like the institute of
electrical institute of electrical
electronics engineers I don't know this
Oliver for I forget right okay
the professional organization for
Electrical and Electronics Engineers
right computer engineers right and so
you know as an engineering organization
they care a lot about understanding
tolerances right they care a lot about
understanding how error creeps into
things because one thing you learn as an
engineers there's no such thing as
perfect right you guys learn that like
your first engineering class I remember
that's mine right there's no such thing
as perfect everything is something plus
or minus some tolerance and when you
build something you have to worry about
how those tolerances stack because that
error can slowly add up right and so
they were concerned about that in the
numbering system they were concerned how
rounding what happens if we have an
actual value that falls between two
points in our number line it's gonna go
here it's gonna go here there's no point
here they were concerned about how that
rounding stacked up and creeped in and
affected computation they were concerned
there be a numbering system right that
can be well understood such that
engineers using computer systems to do
math could understand what the results
meant and so they developed a standard
for floating-point numbers okay and so
there's a couple of classic examples of
numbering systems that had in some way
shape or form problems the bottom line
is if you if you go and do reading on
the web you're gonna find a lot of
examples you know in space programs and
in military applications where numerical
problems cause things to blow up okay in
one way shape or form
cause systems to fail why do you tend to
find it in these applications well these
applications tend to push the limits
right if you're dealing with commercial
aviation we try to keep things nice and
safe although there have occasionally
been problems we have a much
our margin of safety then if we're
exploring you know outer space with an
unmanned probe in that case we just
wanna get as far as we can and collect
all the data we can and if it blows up
there's nobody aboard we'll build a new
one right military applications
sometimes you have to take more risk
because there's risk and getting shot at
right and so you willing to have a
system that might fail a little more
often if it gets you shot at a little
less often you've got to balance the
risks when you're in a hazardous
environment but the bottom line is you
know in NASA with the air in five the
Patriot missile system there were
situations where numerical problems
prevented the system from working and
then things blew up in one case that
cost 500 million in another case 28
people died these things matter if I
look at this number
it shouldn't shock and amaze you that's
a binary number everything is in ones
and zeros only that little subscript -
okay no shock and amazement this over
here is what we call the binary point
like the decimal point but it's a binary
number binary point going from the
binary point to the left we have 2 to
the 0 to the 1 2 squared to the cube
right 1 2 4 8 16 going to the right of
the binary point we have 1/2 1/4 1/8
1/16 right to the negative powers so our
Sun is just the same as it was before
except instead of starting at zero at
zero we started some negative number and
we add up the value of crosshair
positions
ok so if we start here right that's 1/2
that's 1/4 that's why we have one one
eight zero one quarters one one-half one
one one two
no fours and 1/8 the value of this and
decimal is 11 and five-eighths
okay so you know / shifting right still
works okay we have the two to the zero
and to the right we have one over two to
the negative one so dividing by two
still works - you know right shift still
works - divided left shift still works
as a multiply in this particular simple
example if I have something that's all
ones repeating that's a fraction below
one right how small well if I would add
point in this example point zero zero
zero zero zero one then that would
become one right if this is one
repeating forever we say it's an epsilon
away from one of course I can't repeat
forever because why yeah we have a
finite amount of memory so we talked
about Epsilon you know in in this type
of context we're generally talking about
some known small value some small value
that either we've defined as meaningful
in our application or as mathematically
defined based upon the data sizes we
actually have just like with decimal
numbers right in decimal numbers we can
only represent things that can be
represented as sums of powers of 10
binary numbers we can only represent
things that are sums of powers of two
right we had a problem if we were
dealing with like one-third that can't
be represented as a sum of a power of 10
so it's point three repeating okay we
have the same problem with one-third as
it turns out in binary you can look at
this and you can see it's 0 1 0 1 0 1 0
1 0 what the 0 1 repeats forever 1/5 you
can see the 0 1 0 0 1 1 repeats forever
1/10 right still we see a 0 0 1 1
repeats forever
ok what are you looking at
so my suggestion to you I don't like I'm
not gonna work that right now to find
out put it into a computer take a look
print it out in hexadecimal then you'll
know zero X percent X what's that
one-fifth to one tenth is right shifted
by a bit that's correct
look I'm standing two feet from the
slide the ones and zeros all bleed
together so the example is off by a zero
enjoy I didn't expect you guys to do all
the examples the point was that for some
fractions you have bits repeating and
that it can be a pattern of bits that
repeat not just a single bit okay I
Triple E 754 is the floating point
standard it was established from 1985
for all the reasons we talked about
these engineers need to understand what
the tolerances are they need to
understand how much error can creep in
at this point the standard is supported
by all major CPUs why because people who
are doing scientific computation right
need to have a standard they understand
if every processor implements a slightly
different standard it's gonna be really
hard for somebody who's a program are
trying to get something right because
there's a lot of detail that comes into
these situations right it's a nice
standard in the sense that it has
support for running for rounding
underflow and overflow it's not a nice
standard in the sense that it's
floating-point units are very complex it
takes a lot of transistors to get those
things built and get them right
floating-point representation is
essentially a form of scientific
notation okay if you think about
scientific notation remember that for
like fourth grade or something 2.5 times
10 to the third
why do they call scientific notation
scientific notation why did you use it
like in chemistry and physics and yeah
okay so one reason is right in science
you very big numbers and very small
numbers and this effective way to
represent both it's a lot more fun to
have you know two point five times ten
to the negative thirteenth then have to
write out a huge number of zeros what
else is really nice about scientific
notation
think about freshman chemistry class as
a high school student yeah significant
figures right sig figs remember sig figs
they're back it's revenge of the sig
figs today okay
this idea that when you measure things
you know the met number you have right
has a certain number of digits that you
trust right into most of the signs and
you have a certain number of digits you
trust and then when you approximate
right you say I can exactly measure I
can exactly observe this thermometer is
passed the two and it looks like it's
about halfway to three so I'm going to
call two point five I trust the two I'm
estimating the point the the half passed
that the five right and so you have one
estimated digit or something right um
and what was the detail chemistry but
chemistry a little weird right if you
took chemistry class they they really
took the sigfig thing seriously didn't
they they had a special way of rounding
anybody remember how they rounded what
did you do if you had something that you
had you know you've done something that
computation and you had three digits you
know then the computation had three
digits you only allowed two significant
figures you had to get rid of a digit
what you do did you always round up did
you always round down what did you do
yeah
yeah you have you have you have the
basic idea so look if it's less than
half you round down because it's less
than half it's closer to smaller it is
greater than half you round up because
it's more there than not right but if it
is exactly half it's not fair to always
round up because you get a bias you're
taking something that's half and always
making it bigger when really it's just
as close to the smaller number one point
five is every bit as close to one as it
is to two why do we round up to two
that's good for the taxman I guess right
so chemists I think I've I remember
correctly chemist round even there's to
say if I have 0.5 if I have 1.5 I round
two - I round toward the even so I round
from 1.5 up to two but if I have 2.5 I
round down to even instead of going up
to three I go down to two the philosophy
there is that I'm rounding up as often
as I round down so I'm not introducing a
bias does that make sense so in a lot of
ways what we're doing here you're gonna
see he's gonna follow exactly that model
okay this is gonna be base 2 instead of
base 10 all right
but basically what I'm gonna have is I'm
going to have some fraction ok times 2
to some exponent and then it's gonna be
negative or positive
just like sig figs right just like
scientific notation with significant
figures right you know we might have
three-point and decimal and I have three
point five times ten to the third or
negative three point five times ten to
the third now in this notation right
we're going to have one point you know
101 1 101 times 10 to the something or x
- 2 something I'm sorry okay know what
we're gonna actually find is it sort of
interesting right what do we do with
leading zeros by the number if I have
number zero zero one zero do I
care about the leading zeros what do I
do with leading zeros I'm trying to put
something a scientific notation throw
them away right I shift until they're
not there if I have zero zero you know
if I have you know zero zero one zero
that's a ten right well if you think
about binary numbers
this means that everything we represent
in scientific notation in binary except
for zero is going to begin with what one
so actually we don't need to store the 1
because we know it's there that makes
sense either I'm storing zero or begins
with the 1 okay so in representing one
of these numbers I have a fractional
component that's just like the
fractional component for scientific
notations in chemistry class like 2.5
except for the fact we're thinking of it
in binary and we know it begins with the
1 so we're just going to ignore that 1
then we multiply it like before in
scientific notation 2.5 times 10 to the
third now we multiply it by some
exponent except now instead of 10 to
something it's 2 2 to something positive
or negative okay if it's positive right
that's going to make the number bigger
if it's negative that's gonna make the
number of fraction so I have some
fraction times 2 to an exponent and that
whole thing is gonna be negative or
positive as indicated by the sign bit
sign bits on it's negative if it's not
it's not negative does that make sense
so far now we have one small trick I
need to be able to represent a negative
exponent right if I can't represent a
negative exponent what can't I represent
fractions yes how did you say that
fractions exactly right okay so somehow
this exponent needs to be able to
represent these exponent bits to be able
to represent positive and negative
exponents
so remember I said the size the number
of bits in a binary number tells us how
many points we have in a number line
the only decision we get to make is how
we label them the natural way of
labeling these things is from 0 to some
positive number right but we don't want
that because we want to have negative
numbers so we want to shift our labeling
so that 0 is in the middle and we have
some positive numbers and some negative
numbers ok so I want to have about as
many positive numbers as negative
numbers right that seems fair
it's like the way we used to play me
like symmetry right so if I think about
let's say a 3 bit number what is a range
of values of that number just normally
from 0 to what 7 okay so if I do nothing
I have 0 7 but ideally I don't want 0 to
7 okay if I subtract 3 I have negative 3
2 what for if I subtract 4 I have
negative 4 to 3 does that make sense
that's what we call the bias the amount
we're going to subtract to shift our
number line so that 0 is approximately
Center okay now the question is what
should that bias be okay I'll come back
to this in a minute okay
but we have one math this slide attempts
to convince you that you need to do some
weird stuff with math to figure out what
the bias should be here's the thing you
don't we know we want the range to be
approximately even right we want about
as many negative numbers as positive
numbers we know it's not going to be
perfectly even because zero comes out of
which side of the number line the well
the non negative side the pot the
otherwise positive side right so okay if
we look at a number okay
this is a little weird so if we look at
a a tack a bit number there's two say a
4 bit number 5 bit number 6 bit number
let's go back to my 3 bit number a
number that's 0 0 0 through 1 1 1 this
thing suggests that the bias should be 2
to the K minus 1 let's look at that for
a moment 2 to the 3 minus 1 is 2 squared
which is 4 ok so I have a 3 bit number
right which represents 0 to 7 this says
if I look at the 2 to the K the bias you
know that part that's gonna be 4 or
about halfway right would you agree
halfway in that range is gonna be 3 or 4
we all agree so to the K by itself right
2 to the K minus 1 is gonna be 4
if I give you a 4 bit number what's the
range of a 4 bit number 1 2 4 8 the
high-order bit is 8
what's my biggest number 15 it's 0 to 15
okay so what's gonna be about halfway
seven or eight right well if I take 2 to
the K 2 to the 4 minus 1 that's 2 to the
3 that's 8 right we agree y bydd 0 bit 1
bit 2 bit 3 that's the value of my high
water bit which equals all my low order
bits plus 1 does that make sense so my
bias as we've decided to do this you
know my choice between having my bias be
slightly higher and slightly lower what
choice are we making here if the bias is
2 to the K minus 1 power minus 1 what
have we chosen to do with the bias make
it slightly more than half or slightly
less than half slightly less than half
right so that's what we know given any
number all this says is the bias is
going to be slightly less than half
can't be exactly half we're going to go
in favor of slightly less than half so
if I tell you I have a 32 bit number
what's the bias going to be well 2 to
the 31 minus 1 but don't get wrapped up
in that instead think like what's the
biggest value this number can have
what's a little less than half of that
and that'll make sense because just
shifting the number line by half way
okay since our bias is a little less
than half we're going to have slightly
fewer negative numbers and positive
numbers does that make sense so you can
see that here from negative 126 to 127
or negative 1022 to 1023 do you see that
so that's how we're gonna represent our
exponent when we think about our
exponents okay if we need an exponent of
4 we're not actually going
store for in this exponent field we're
going to adjust it by the bias that way
we have the ability to represent a
negative number um there are a few
different I Triple E standard single
precision double precision and extended
precision these are how the bits break
out okay single precision is 23 bits for
the fraction eight bits for the exponent
one bit for design double precision 52
bits for the fraction eleven bits for
the exponent one bit for the sign
extended precision 64 bits for the
fraction 15 bits for the exponent one
bit to the side okay
so we've said we want things to work a
little differently
I'm just give ahead a little bit here
again I'm never goodbye playing never
good playing with the rules there we go
we've said we want things to work a
little differently right we want a lot
of points very close to zero one of the
points to be very close together as we
get farther away from zero we want the
points to be more distant so we can get
to bigger numbers greater precision for
small numbers less precision for big
numbers okay
so the way we get more points like this
right is not that we get more points we
have the same number points we just
label them closer together so you can
see that there's a pretty big dividing
line there okay there's what we call
normalized and denormalize numbers the
denormalized numbers are very close to
zero the normalized numbers are farther
away the denormalize numbers give us
things that are very close to each other
the normalized numbers give us things
that are farther away okay so let's take
a look at normalized values normalized
values are going to exist when the
exponent bits are not all zero and the
exponent bits are not all one those are
going to be used for special things okay
and we'll talk about that in a minute
the exponent is going to be encoded as
the actual exponent we compute to do the
whatever - the bias why - the bias again
that lets us have the negative part of
the range so we write if I compute a
bias if I compute an exponent of four
and I have a bias of something what I'm
recording is four minus the bias in the
actual bit field okay we talked about
why the bias is to K minus one slightly
less than half okay okay we already
talked about the fact that you know in a
binary number I'm gonna be leading with
a 1 right because I'm not gonna shift my
zeroes away so I'm not gonna bother to
store the leading one it's implied if
I'm try five I'm thinking one point one
one zero one times two to the fourth I'm
gonna store point zero one one x to the
fourth and when I go to interpret it I'm
going to interpret it as one point zero
one one times two to the fourth so we
don't actually store that leading one we
just assume it okay so if I'm trying to
encode 15 to 13 binary point zero I
write this out in binary okay I shift
until I have a leading one I count the
number of times I shifted and that's my
exponent right now my exponent is 13 but
I'm not gonna record a 13 into my
exponent bits I'm going to adjust it by
my bias okay my exponents 13 my bias is
127 I'm gonna store a 140 okay why do I
add a 140 because I'm gonna subtract a
140 when I interpret it why do I have to
subtract things when I interpret it to
get my range to back up so part of it
can become negative okay so I
start out with my number and I write it
out in binary I shift to get a leading
one and keep track of the number of
times I shifted that's my power of two
exponent I take that and add it to my to
my bias I'm adding it to my bias now so
I subtract my bias later which is what
gives me the shift of my range I store
my exponent plus bias in the exponent
field
okay 140 in binary is one zero zero zero
one one zero zero boom okay this is my
fractional components I ignore the
leading one it's one point whatever is
here and I write out the rest if I run
out of room because I have more bits of
my fractional component than I have here
what do I do
what's that okay well for the moment
let's just say I throw the extras away
and then we're gonna get to the rounding
fair enough okay
now this is what's called normalized
numbers remember that on my number line
the normalized numbers are the ones
farther from zero that are giving me the
big steps that let me capture a large
range okay denormalized numbers exist
where the exponent is all zero okay if
the exponent is zero okay then I'm
dealing with this denormalized range in
the demobilize reign range my exponent
by E is actually going to be is actually
going to be zero minus my bias okay what
that's a little confusing I think that's
probably the most confusing thing in
this deck okay my exponent is held at
zero okay do you see that the exponent
bits are always zero I'm close to zero
I'm dealing with a fraction I'm not
bigger than one here right
we'll deal with the details in a minute
but I'm dealing with a fraction all
right
so if I do that I make my exponent zero
minus the bias because that makes my
denormalized range meet my normalized
range I'll show you that in a second
okay if I didn't do that then the two
ranges wouldn't meet I'd have a gap in
my number line okay so now I'm going to
assume a leading zero instead of a
leading one I'm gonna shift until I have
a zero point one something okay so now
that's my fraction and then I go from
there
the thing about the denormalized range
is that because my exponent is fixed my
numbers are spaced the same distance
apart does that make sense if I'm
changing my exponent making it bigger
and bigger and bigger the points on my
number line are getting farther and
farther away if I hold my exponent
constant then the points in the number
line are equally spaced that's why this
is called the denormalized range it's
not normalized it's not stretched okay
if my exponent is all ones this is a
special thing you say you remember an
integer math we had all this weirdness
if we wrapped around we overflowed or we
under flowed that doesn't work for
engineers if it gets so hot right that
you can't compute it it's not okay to
say it's cold right we can't point out
thermometer at this you know that the
Sun and say it's it's you know it's you
know you know it's it's you know
absolute zero Kelvin or something right
just doesn't work that way we can't wrap
around like that so what happens with I
Triple E math is that if you overflow
there's a bit that says we've overflowed
and it keeps track of the sign positive
overflow or negative overflow positive
or negative infinity okay
is also something called not a number
it's what you get if you divide by zero
or take the square root of negative of
negative one or something like that
where you just can't represent the
answer and again it keeps track of the
sign and so there's a positive man and a
negative net the really bizarre thing
and this is bizarre is that there's
actually a positive and negative zero
it's unavoidable because 0 is the bit
pattern all zeros right but the sign bit
can be on or off
so really bizarrely there's actually a
positive and negative zero where the the
the non negative zero is the same as the
integer zero all bits are zeros okay so
our number line looks like this
the denormalized range which is equally
spaced the normalized range we have big
spaces negative infinity positive zero
infinity and then man you can't really
say that like not a numbers positive or
negative there's an N on the negative
side there's an N on the positive side
but like is the square root of negative
one positive or negative like that
doesn't work right
and so then you can call it negative
name I'm positive man but like a
mathematician will get upset yes you
what else do you gonna do how many bits
are you gonna do going to dedicate to
representing things that you can't know
if you'd if you're trying to compute the
trajectory for a missile and you end up
with an an where do you want that
missile to land right I mean you better
know that you don't know
um okay so you asked me why is Nana
range rather than a specific number and
the IP the honest answer to that
question the downside for you that
questions I don't know I think the
answer is that once she started doing
special things it makes it a very hard
to implement in hardware and be
sometimes very very high yeah it makes
it hard to implement in hardware I think
is what it comes to the rules become
complex and it becomes hard to get right
and that's a bad day that's the best
answer I can suspect so this becomes a
lot easier with examples here is an 8
bit number there is no such thing as an
I Triple E 8 bit standard but we're
gonna follow an I Triple E like standard
we have 4 bits for the exponent and 3
bits for the fraction 1 bit for the sign
bit this slide I think is worth a ton
use me this tie the slide I think is
worth the time ok so we see our sign bit
we see our exponent bits we see our
fraction bits okay if you look at this
you see where we go from the largest
denormalized number to the smallest
normalized number okay when does this
happen this happens when the 1 1 1
becomes 1 0 0 0 do you see that you
remember I told you that the bias is 0
minus the bias because it makes the
number line continuous this is what I
was talking about if that by is for
anything other than what it is the two
normalized range wouldn't meet the
denormalized range nicely like this
where you can see that as we go from 0
right to the all zeros in a 1 we add 1
5/12 right add 1 to that we get 1 0 to 5
12 right add 1 to that we get 3 5/12
right four or five twelve five five
twelve right add 1 to that we get 6 5 12
7 5 12 and then even as we transition
to the normalized range we do that by
adding still one five twelve okay so
it's a nice smooth transition there so
there are several interesting points
right the closest point to zero has the
bit pattern all zeros into one right the
largest denormalized number has all ones
to the fractional component nothing for
the exponent right the smallest the
normalized number has a one for the
exponent and zero for all the fractions
okay you know the closest to you know
two one below one right you know we can
see a bit pattern for I don't know
that's particularly interesting the
largest normalize number right again we
can look at this bit pattern and we can
see it's all ones here right all ones
here zero here why if that becomes a one
it becomes infinity okay smooth
transitions really an interesting
observation okay and we can zoom in here
and see what we mean about the
denormalized range having equal space
things right and the normalized range
getting spread out floating point zero
is the same as integer zero as long as
we're talking about the non negative
zero so this means that we can almost
use the unsigned integer comparison we
can almost compare an unsigned you know
an unsigned integer zero to an integer
zero but we must consider the negative
zero versus zero
Nan's are problematic of course what do
you do is something that's not a number
otherwise we're pretty okay now let's
talk about rounding
so first we want to understand what is
if we had a more precision than we have
what is the exact result or at least the
result in more precision than we
actually need okay
then we need to make it fit okay if we
can't write we need to we need around
that so it fits in the fractional
component right there's to say we need
to lose fractional bits in order to make
it work we talked about rounding okay we
talked about rounding towards zero and
away from zero okay so think about the
case of a dollar $40 $60 fifty to fifty
negative 150 okay if I have a dollar
sixty and I round toward zero right
that's gonna take the dollar sixty down
to a dollar right it's gonna take
negative a dollar fifty down to it you
know it's gonna take negative fifty down
to a negative one dollar closer to zero
note that this became bigger more
positive by fifty cents right and this
became smaller by sixty cents that's
because the rule is round toward zero
right in that case which is rounding in
opposite directions depending upon which
way you are in the number line okay the
non negative side is a number line
you're rounding down the negative side
of the number line you're rounding up
okay if we always round down always
round toward negative infinity right
then we're always rounding you know
always rounding to the negative side of
the number line right then we see a buck
forty becomes dollar a buck sixty
becomes dollar buck 50 becomes dollar
250 becomes two dollars and negative 150
now goes negative two things were always
going left the negative side of the
number line if we round up it's the
opposite right buck forty becomes two
buck 50 becomes two buck 15 becomes two
to 50 becomes three right on the
negative side of the number line
negative 150 becomes negative one why
we're rounding in the direction of the
greater value positive infinity the
default rounding mode
in I triple-a is to the nearest even and
it's to the nearest even for the same
reason okay that it was to the nearest
even in your chemistry class to avoid
that bias if we always round up we
always round down and we always round in
some weird way
eventually the always is going to
generate a bias yeah
that wasn't fun at all a jump when I
wake you up that's the deal ah let's
raise alive nah I think everybody here
is to sleep was already in the semester
all right so the default rounding mode
and I Triple E is going to be to round
toward the even okay so if we look at
this and we're trying to round this
number to two decimal points it's clear
that it should be rounded down
everything after that is less than half
in this case okay it should be rounded
up it's half plus something closer to
the bigger number in this case it's
exactly half oh it's not closer to the
bigger number any closer the bigger
number there's a smaller number or vice
versa so what do we do we round toward
the even given the choice between
rounding down to one point two three and
rounding up to one point two four what
do we do two fours even we round up okay
here one point to 400 exactly halfway
given the choice between rounding down
to one point two four and up to one
point two five we round down to one
point two four in one case we round it
up in one case we rounded down that's
how we broke the bias in binary it's
sort of more fun because that one
represents exactly half so one followed
by all zeroes is half that's the case we
even write a one followed by anything is
more than half we round up alright so if
I take a look at this one zero binary
point zero zero zero one zero and I want
to round to two digits I cover this up
and I ask is that more is it is it less
than half greater than half or exactly
half well it's less than half because
that's not a one round down no question
asked okay here 10.00 cover up well
that's clearly more than half because
it's half plus something I round up ten
point zero one in this case I cover it I
end up with exactly half okay
now the choice is between rounding down
to 10.1 one losing the half or rounding
up to 11.00 okay
well the question is what am I going to
do I'm gonna round toward even is that
even know it has a 1 in the ones place
right so that's gonna have to get
rounded up to 11.00 that case confuses
people a little bit right people for
some reason want to get into this case
and think that it's somehow between you
know 10.1 one and 10.1 0.10 is going the
wrong direction right okay here we have
10.10 100 so when I cover this I'm in
that half case again my choice is now
between rounding down to 10.10 or up to
10.1 one point one one has a 1 in the
rightmost place so it's odd
so I round down to 10.10 yes
choose two and 70 cases like rounding
19.5 isn't oranges are like apples
aren't they I guess help me out this is
that if I have ninety-nine point you
know nine nine five right or something
then I'm gonna end up adding a little
bit to round up in the same way we do it
over here
exactly okay um floating point
multiplication what to say if we're
doing floating point multiplication it's
not really in the abstract anything
complicated we do exactly the same thing
we find the actual true result okay and
then we get it represented as a floating
point number we shift until we have the
right form we find that bias we record
our our exponent we record as much of
the fraction as we can
rounding even these that's what the
Tripoli's I Triple E standard requires
okay
[Music]
so you know if we're too big we shift
you know we shifted right too small we
shift to the left that changes their
exponent we overflow if it's out of
range we make our fraction fit rounding
is necessary okay floating point and C
float is a single precision number
according to the I Triple E standard
devil's gonna be a double precision
number if we're casting between a a
double or a float in an INT okay it's
obviously the case that if I go from a
double the float to an int the int
cannot handle the fractional convinced
right if I float is 1.5 and I'm trying
to cast that to an end it can't handle
the half it's an int okay so it's going
to truncate the fractional part it's not
going to round I Triple E standard about
this rounding even only works within the
I Triple E floating point space if I
take a floating point number and I try
to stick it into an integer it's not
gonna fit and what doesn't fit it's
gonna fall out okay so it's gonna be
truncation what happens if you have not
a number who knows
it'll probably turn out to be team n
okay what if I try to cast an INT into a
double that's okay because as it turns
out a double is much wider than an int
right twice the width so the full
integer component of an INT
can fit into the integer component of a
double I will not lose anything okay if
I try to go from an int to a float now I
have a problem because an int and a
float are the same size but the float
loses the bit to the sign and loses a
bunch of bits to the exponent so the
integer component is smaller so I can't
actually fit it into a float okay and so
when that happens it's going to enter a
floating-point number which is going to
enter the I Triple E rules so it's gonna
round according to the rounding mode
round even okay
what to say
floating-point numbers are painful if
you actually care about getting things
exactly right right I coached the
programming here from any teammate here
for many many years and one of the
classic ways that we that you know CMU
you know blew problems that we otherwise
should have gotten right was we would
use floating-point arithmetic and we
were asked does X equal equal Y and we
would do computation here and
computation here and they were
equivalent but because the math was done
in different ways the rounding happened
differently and so they weren't exactly
equal they were close because one of
them stirred out with small numbers and
blew up and got big and then got small
again and rounded in one particular way
that way another one of them started out
with lard and uh numbers and multiply
them rounded more and then multiply the
small numbers and got smaller and lost
more precision right and then if you do
these in different orders you may lose
the same amount of precision but lose it
in different ways okay now you're
rounding all that happens weird so with
with floating-point numbers you really
shouldn't use equal equal you really
should subtract the two and ask if
they're less than Epsilon if the
difference is less than some epsilon
right this is a natural thing to do for
engineers because engineers are used to
thinking in terms of tolerances right
you know keep the washing machine drawer
door locked until the water level is
less than X not until the water levels
absolutely zero because it may be a
little bit left at the bottom right
unlock the stove after cleaning when the
temperature is below blah not when the
temperature is exactly the same as the
room that's good enough to be safe right
the two sensors right you know that are
measuring air flow right should be
within some epsilon of each other
they're not perfectly calibrated
but if they're more different than that
maybe the plane's wing is gonna stall
okay so engineers naturally think in
terms of tolerances but computer
scientists sometimes you know we're used
to discrete math we don't think about
tolerances right one is one zero zero
Dada right and so we have a hard time
with this type of thing and so you know
we think of math as you know all you
know as we learned and it just and as we
use it and so we tend to forget about
that and so you know it really actually
when you're doing floating-point code
right you shouldn't you shouldn't ask
does it actually equal zero you should
ask is it close enough to zero for my
purpose okay other things that happen is
you have to pay attention to how things
round after I guessed were the end of my
undergraduate and as I was beginning
grad school I did research in neural
networks for a while and I took this
neural network that we were built built
as a neural network according to a paper
and I demonstrated to my bosses when we
do that great you know you have this
this great implementation there's a
neural network architecture now you know
try to solve this problem with it okay
here I did here's my results well great
how long did it take you nine hours okay
that's not good enough
go optimize that codes you can you know
it can take less than you know less than
a minute okay and so I did a whole bunch
of optimization and then I came back
like three weeks later and I'm like like
that good news and bad news for you okay
well what's the good news I can do it in
about 45 seconds what's the bad news it
never actually converges you know and to
which one of the bosses replied well if
I wanted the wrong answer I could do it
much faster turned around to his
keyboard and did printf hello world
and so we talked about this for a while
and you know we looked at the results
and look at some of the numbers and some
of the cases and whatever and one of my
bosses said well you know it looks like
there might be some type of numerical
analysis problem there he you know
are you using floats for this I'm like
yeah he's like I think you haven't have
a numerical analysis problem I didn't
understand what he meant and then I went
back and looked at it and learned
something about floats and realized that
what I done I gotten to the point where
I drove values down to where they were
really close to zero and noise took over
the way I did the multiplication right
generated noise that was then dominating
the computation and that's why beyond a
certain point I actually couldn't get a
viable result I couldn't get enough
convergence for our purposes and so I
rewrote it using integers and fixed
point and so I've seen this crop up you
know a lot in a lot of different cases
so when you do the same computation in
different ways you may you may end up in
different situations a plus B plus C may
not equal you know a plus people say
okay yeah so here we have a plus B plus
C with B plus C plus D and so here we
have B plus C and here we have B plus C
right the compiler may not be able to
take that out and do the B plus C once
okay we look at this and say okay the
compiler can do temporary equals B plus
C a plus 10 B plus D plus temp right
because to us B plus C is B plus C I can
do that computation just once but the
problem is here it's a it's a plus B
plus C and here it's B plus C plus D and
it may actually round differently when I
do the B plus C plus D then the a plus B
plus C right so if I try to take that
out what could happen here is the a plus
B
Plus see I mean may not round the same
as a plus quantity B plus C okay um
we've got more puzzles okay and again I
don't think me doing the puzzles is
helpful to you I think you need to do
the puzzles okay and then talk about
with the move your friends right and
then come to office hours if you need
help but just take a quick look all
right X is a X is an integer
f is a floating-point number D is a
double okay so I have some integer
equals I take X which is an integer I
cast it as a float when I do that am i
guaranteed to maintain the same level of
precision no an int X and a float are
the same size right but a float has to
be able to as bits that are dedicated to
maintaining the fractions so this is
going to get rounded as X becomes a
float when I cast it back from a float
to an int that loses nothing but I've
already lost going from the into the
float so at this point my X here does
not necessarily equal my original X it
rounded when X became a float
make sense okay here when I go from into
a double I'm okay because the double is
twice as wide as an int and it has
enough integer bits to store a whole
integer so I lose nothing going from an
integer to a double and I certainly lose
nothing taking those same bits back out
and putting them into an integer since
it started out as an integer I didn't
have any fractions to lose so that'll be
okay going from a float to a double I'm
fine
right it doubles twice as big as a float
going from a double back to a float I'm
still fine okay
coming from a double to a float
obviously not okay
a double was twice as big right more
precision and so I'm gonna let you take
you to sort of take them from there one
question is like if you think about this
I'll give you a hint as to how to think
of it I don't know what you solve them
from there if I take F and I make it
negative and then I make it negative
again is that the same as F the hint is
it is the same if the number one is
symmetric the hint is it's not the same
if the number line is not symmetric
because then if I'm somewhere over here
that's not representable over here
I could lose something and then once
I've lost it
I don't get it back going the other way
okay
2/3 versus 2 divided by 3.0 again I'm
going to let you do that but what I'm
going to note is that this is integer
division and this is not because that's
a floating-point number okay okay we see
something there so let you think about
that you know here if D is less than
zero
does that imply that D times two is also
less than zero this is a question about
rounding mode with integers it didn't
right because if I took a negative
number and I multiply it by something
and I under float it it became positive
the question is here does that happen or
does something else happen think about
the special States that we have in I
Triple E numbers to present prevent
something that gets too hot from looking
cold or something gets too cold from
looking hot if I if I have some double I
know it's greater than some
floating-point number does that imply
that negative of that floating-point
number is greater than negative of that
double okay well what you want to notice
there is this is D greater
a nap right so this is D my double to
the right of my floating-point number
okay mmm D magnitude greater than F and
on this side of the number line it's
negative F greater than negative D okay
so in this case that sign is backwards
right negative 1 is greater than
negative 2 okay so that's what you want
to pay attention to and understanding
that and now the question is is D times
D greater than zero well think about it
normally we think about a positive D and
say okay if I have a 4 4 times 4 is
greater than 0 right and I'd say the
same is also true with negative numbers
right negative 4 times negative 4 the
negatives are gonna cancel out but now
the question is is that going to work
out in the case of floating point
numbers in the case of integers not
necessarily right because I could I
could overflow become negative think
about how I Triple E handles that case
does D plus F minus D equal F will again
to most people sure right we've
associativity community D plus F minus D
is the same as D minus D plus F plus F
is equal to AB but remember the case of
rounding and although the community of
it associated properties are
approximately true and floating-point
numbers they're not necessarily exactly
true so think about what that means in
this case I'm summary I Triple E
floating point standard has clear
mathematical properties it represents
numbers in the form of scientific
notation
specifically base to scientific notation
it's great because one can reason about
the operations independent of
implementation if I know that a
processor implements the I Triple E
standard I don't have to worry about
which algorithms it uses to do math okay
it's not the same as the arithmetic you
learned in math class that approximation
means that associativity and
distributive Atene community don't
necessarily work the same way which
makes life difficult for compilers why
does it make life difficult for
compilers you and I might look at
something and say oh I can remove this
common sub-expression the results will
be close enough to the original for my
purposes but the compiler doesn't know
your purposes so it can't do that so
when it comes to floating point math
compilers can't do some of the forms of
mathematical optimization they would do
with integer operations even though it
might be fine with us because they can't
break things that were correct before
they started ok one more thing I
actually want to talk about you guys
flew with the Intel F div bug anybody
heard of it on the Pentium pending bug
so the it's just a classic story about
floating points so floating point math
and a processor happens in ways very
very different than you might think it
would okay long division takes a lot of
iterations okay it's not a really good
way of making things consistent in a
processor okay it's not a good way of
making things go fast in a processor so
they years if you learned
Taylor and Maclaurin series like in some
calculus class right they use series
basically to understand what the results
will be and have tables of partial
fractions you know and when they were
and these things worked out years ago
okay and so when they were building the
the Pentium processor Intel's new
flagship processor at the time there was
an intern who was given the job of
loading this table onto the tape
basically of loading this into the the
new processor design and his Perl script
had a head of bug and was off by one and
it went unnoticed through their
validation and so every Pentium
processor on earth was built with
certain you know with the ability to
have incorrect results for certain
divisions and as I remember and I'm Fabi
here I think was a professional Georgia
Tech who is maybe a physicist or some
scientist that have been doing these
really precise experiments and the
graduate students were running them on
this new equipment and the results were
really bad and they spent this huge than
they weren't correct right they spent
this huge amount of time checking their
code and then checking the compiler and
then eventually they came to the
conclusion that must be the processor
and you know Intel thought they were
nuts of course there's no problem how
processors are like whatever right and
then eventually they just took the
simple case and did like all the all the
division cases right and then compare
them to the actual results and found the
F did bug and Intel basically had to
replace every penny and they sold
classic stories you can look it up on
the web
any other questions hang on yes
the floating point division is
associative between float to floating
point numbers so I can flip the left and
right in isolation it will be the same
yes yes why not use a second sign bit
instead of a bias the reason we do the
second we use the bias instead of the
second sign bit is because it makes the
number line smooth otherwise the number
line would break you'd have this weird
discontinuity where you couldn't look at
the number line and transition smoothly
from one to the next does that make
sense and the reason this works is
because we fixed the bias in one case
right to match the bias the other so the
fixed bias equals the bias of the end of
the of the normalized range does that
make sense okay any other questions have
a great day everybody
Subtitles End: mo.dbxdb.com